<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The late covenant asserted. 1. That it is in whole and in part agreeable to sacred scripture, holy, just, and good. 2. That Oxford-covenant is abominable, contrary to law, right reason, good sense; whereby it appeares, what keepers the lords of the world are of the scales and soules there. 3. That the protestation two years agon, and covenant now, are both one for substance; and a sweet agreement betweene all foure, protestation, covenant, oath of supremacy and allegeance. ... 9. A petition of the wild of Kent, and like places, shewing the sense of the inhabitants there: the root of all these mischiefes, the divine bishops, and their service-booke, which commands another treatise. 10. Oxfords covenant is annexed to the end, and the reason given in the next leafe. Licensed and entred to order.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88762</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871146</idno>
  <idno type="VID">159067</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942153</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E250_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212537</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871146</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871146e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88762)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 43:E250[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The late covenant asserted. 1. That it is in whole and in part agreeable to sacred scripture, holy, just, and good. 2. That Oxford-covenant is abominable, contrary to law, right reason, good sense; whereby it appeares, what keepers the lords of the world are of the scales and soules there. 3. That the protestation two years agon, and covenant now, are both one for substance; and a sweet agreement betweene all foure, protestation, covenant, oath of supremacy and allegeance. ... 9. A petition of the wild of Kent, and like places, shewing the sense of the inhabitants there: the root of all these mischiefes, the divine bishops, and their service-booke, which commands another treatise. 10. Oxfords covenant is annexed to the end, and the reason given in the next leafe. Licensed and entred to order.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed on this day, a day of trouble, and of rebuke, and of blasphemies, 1643. for Thomas Vnderhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 14th. 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Oaths --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159067:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE LATE COVENANT ASSERTED.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> That it is in whole and in part agreeable to sacred Scripture, holy, just, and good.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> That <hi>Oxford</hi>-Covenant is abominable, contrary to Law, Right Reason, good Sense; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appeares, what <hi>Keepers</hi> the Lords of the world are of the <hi>Scales</hi> and <hi>Soules</hi> there.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> That the <hi>Protestation</hi> two yeares agon, and <hi>Covenant</hi> now, are both one for substance; and a sweet agreement between all foure, <hi>Protestation, Covenant, Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegeance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> That the five <hi>Observations</hi> sent us from <hi>Oxford</hi> upon our <hi>Covenant,</hi> are wicked and blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous; The first cleane contrary to Law; The fourth most contrary to <hi>sense;</hi> The fifth crosseth Reason; The second and third blasphemeth the <hi>way</hi> of all <hi>Israel</hi> in their <hi>warre,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> warranted by God Himselfe in two most <hi>famous Cases,</hi> set down here, which will cleare our <hi>Case</hi> as the noon day; Wherein these particulars are observable in passage; That Faith has a Bottom where Reason has none; That Gods People may fall in a lawfull warre, That they shall be Remembred in a low estate; That it is as impossible to accommodate a Peace, as it is to bring the two <hi>Poles</hi> together, <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> which stand at an eternall opposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Cleare satisfaction given to all Objections, (I say all, because a Reasonable man shall not find what more to object) against the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>taking-up of Armes;</hi> The Oath of Supremacy and Allegeance binds us to it; The Kings Vow and taking the Sacrament upon it, is no more, but what the Lady <hi>Mary,</hi> before shee was Queen, had taken, and all the Papists do take, Rebells and Traitors all to the King and his three Kingdomes.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> An infallible way to finde out an <hi>Holy way,</hi> and an <hi>Holy warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8.</hi> One Objection Answered touching the Tumults caused by the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> A Petition of the <hi>wild of Kent,</hi> and like places, shewing the <hi>sense</hi> of the Inhabitants there: The Root of all these mischiefes, The <hi>Divine Bishops,</hi> and their <hi>Service-Booke,</hi> which Commands another Treatise.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10. Oxfords Covenant</hi> is annexed to the end, and the Reason given in the next leafe.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psalm. 25.10.</hi> &amp; <hi>103.17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>All the Paths of the <hi>Lord</hi> are mercy and truth, unto such as keepe his Covenant.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psalm. 74.20, 21, 22, 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Have respect unto the Covenant for &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Licensed and entred according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed on this day, a day of Trouble, and of Rebuke, and of Blasphemies, 1643. for</hi> Thomas Ʋnderhill.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:159067:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159067:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have at the end (to use the Observators clean language) set down the <hi>text with his Cōment,</hi> (i. e.) for I would be understood) I have set down Oxfords Covenant, as he hath ours, that the Reader may the better observe my <hi>Comment</hi> upon it; too brief, I confesse, yet I beleeve, I have set such a <hi>glosse</hi> upon it, that will set it out very ill-favouredly, and make it appear very detestable, as indeed it is. And had I had time and space for it, I should have made the wickednesse of this Covenant more apparant, for I should have prosecuted these heads more fully, first; That <hi>Perniciosissimam contradictionem,</hi> that monstrous and pernicious contradiction of the hand and tongue; <hi>They will re-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stablish peace in the kingdom;</hi> and swear they will do it, who <hi>have taken peace from the earth,</hi> &amp; swear they will never give it back again. Blessed be <hi>God,</hi> we are not at their allowance. They swear again, &amp; forswear, <hi>They bear Arms, that his Majesties Subjects may fully enioy their liberty and property, according to the Law of the Land.</hi> Very well, but see, what a <hi>Comment</hi> their hands have made upon this text! The righteous God hath <hi>smitten His hand</hi> at this, and his curse shall pursue these execrable — Theeves, Robbers, Murtherers; these roaring Lyons; their Princes are such, saies the <hi>Lord:</hi> and He saies also, for He is sought unto night and day for this thing, He <hi>will persecute them with His Tempest: and make them afraid with His storme,</hi> When He hath cleansed and <hi>whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> His people by these <hi>scullions,</hi> for that must be done first. Amen.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I should have noted, <hi>Insulsam contradictionem,</hi> their absurd contradiction in very <hi>termes</hi> and words; <hi>not obliged by any Acts of State made by the Kings Maiestie [solely:]</hi> yet ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged and sworn too, not to take <hi>or bear Arms, but by the expresse warrant of his Maiestie; or by Authority iustly derived from his Maiesties immediate warrant.</hi> See! not <hi>solely,</hi> and yet <hi>immediately</hi> from his Majestie; <hi>Justly,</hi> and yet derived from his immediate warrant, most <hi>uniustly.</hi> The <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servator</hi> must observe here a contradiction <hi>in terminis, non-sense</hi> and <hi>blasphemy</hi> altogether, which I shall observe and make good in due place.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a most notorious <hi>Soloecisme</hi> in State policy, which was quite forgotten, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it now, it is this; If the <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> nay if the <hi>Commons</hi> (the Nobles may forget themselves, and the <hi>publique,</hi> minding their <hi>private</hi> onely to maintain their <hi>Peerage</hi>) if the <hi>Commons,</hi> as the heads of the Tribes, each of whom do stand for their Thousands, obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Ship of the State falling upon a Rock, where it will dash to peeces, shall <hi>ioyntly</hi> give their help to <hi>steer</hi> it off, to save the Ship and themselves; Their endeavour shall be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, if the master Pilot be drunk, or asleep, and cannot; ignorant, and cares not; conceited, and beleeves not; or wilfull and will not give his consent. <hi>Without his Maiesties expresse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</hi> This saies the <hi>Lord-Keeper</hi> is Law now, but never before now since the world stood.</p>
            <p>But now they swear and vow it is good law at Oxford, so mad they are, or drunk rather; for it is against the law of Nature, against the Law of Nations, against the <hi>Supreme Law,</hi> the safetie of the people. There is no such law in a <hi>Cockboat</hi> neither, or <hi>Pinnace,</hi> nor in your great ships: If the Master Pilote be drunk there, yet he hath his <hi>Mate:</hi> if both be drunk, as sometimes they are, yet in a tempest every man to his work, and all to save the ship for save that, and save all. I will repeate this, and adde a Maxime; when the ship is in danger all are at work, and all to save the ship; and the <hi>Pilot</hi> will not censure them as having their own ends; he will not drown for them, but drown they must, and he too, if they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not save the ship. The maxime is, <hi>A Community can have no private end to mislead it, and make it d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>structive to it self.</hi> To <hi>withdraw</hi> now from this <hi>Community</hi> (the Parliament our Representatives) is next doore to a <hi>with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rawing</hi> from, and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing</hi> God H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mself; nay, it is a plain renouncing of Him: and warring against him. Yet I will not conclude, here, that no honest man hath taken this Covenant <hi>I</hi> do not know what fear may do, and sore oppression, such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s is exercised at Oxford, which has made wise men <hi>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and Christians turn Turks: But this I will conclude he that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes it as the <hi>Observator</hi> hath done willingly (I cannot say <hi>advisedly</hi>) he is <hi>monstrous</hi> in his ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment, and a most notorious — in practise. I have said, what I intend here, and should have been enlarged elsewhere.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:159067:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, the beginning shews, that the <hi>end</hi> should shave been with it in the same sheet; it was so desired and intended. But matter fell-in, and the substance of the work was so minded, that the <hi>form</hi> and <hi>fashion</hi> was a little neglected: good Reason why? for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Christ is marred now, according to the power in the hands of the sonnes of Pride; and why should we look after formes and fashions? Though yet, haply, things might have been better digested upon after thoughts, had there been time and space for them: This will suffice thee; I intented my very soul to be short and compact for thy sake. It could not be; I am large, yet me thinks, not large enough, but for thy sake however, and fuller satisfaction, which truly my soul desires; and then thou wilt say I desire it heartily. I have not accounted the losse of spirits for thy sake; Do not think too much of thy labour to read what is so heartily intended for thy own sake. Here is now, besides what thou wilt have towards the close, a <hi>second Epistle,</hi> whereby thou wilt perceive, I am an earnest sutor. Indeed I am, That thou wouldst read and consider what thou readest; for thy souls sake, for Gods sake, Whom thou shouldst love above thy soul, do so, read and consider. Thou hast need of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thy eyes, and to anoint them with <hi>Eye</hi>-salve, <hi>that thou mayest see.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> give it thee, and us all, even this Annointing. Thou wilt meet here with two <hi>crosse Covenants,</hi> doubtlesse the strangest thing that ever was heard in the world. Nay thou wilt meet towards the end with a Vow and a Sacrament upon it, for the maintenance of the <hi>true Protestant Religion;</hi> all is for confirmation. I remember now, and I should tremble: A Vow and a Sacrament both hath been taken to confirm the heart and hand in the prosecution of the most horrid and hellish designes that ever were invented. O the patience of God! I go on. Thou wilt meet with <hi>Observations</hi> also, as contrary as the Covenants are, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> as hell is to heaven. The Scholar in Oxford is confident, that by his Observations, he hath made (he knows not how many) <hi>Proselytes.</hi> See how conceited a fool is! he is alwayes so. As sure as we live the contrarie is true; their <hi>Covenant</hi> (which he sent us) his <hi>Observations</hi> upon ours, are such, as that he, who reads them, and gives his heart to understand, will fly from that <hi>Covenant,</hi> as from that his soul most hateth, (Cane pejus &amp; Angue,) as from a mad Dogge or fiery Serpent. I have made Observations here also; But I am not such a fool, as to boast, unlesse I could, as a wise man can, boast in the <hi>Lord all the day long, even now,</hi> the <hi>day of Jacobs troubles,</hi> and hath his songs also for the night of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions. I cannot boast, I have intreated thee again and again, as thou lovest thy Countrey, Truth, Peace there, &amp;c. and that, which should be the Crown and Glory of thy reioycing, the <hi>Gospel;</hi> as thou lovest thy life, the life of thy life, <hi>thy eternall soul,</hi> that inestimable treasure; Consider well what thou readest, and apply thy self to Him still, who giveth understanding to the simple, and <hi>teacheth the humble His way;</hi> Cast thy self down at His feet; there the <hi>Elders cast their Crowns;</hi> then He will take thee up, and guide thee <hi>by His counsell;</hi> No matter what way He goes, whether through thick or thinne, as we sometimes say; through rough-wayes or plain; through low bottoms, or high and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanous places, no matter what way, so long as <hi>God</hi> leads thee by His hand, It is abundantly sufficient, <hi>He will bring thee to Glory.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:159067:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE LATE <hi>VOW</hi> AND <hi>COVENANT,</hi> FROM The vain Clamours and Cavils of the Ignorant: The Blasphemous <hi>Observations</hi> sent to us very lately from <hi>Leichfeilds</hi> Presse in OXFORD. Herein is cleared also, That the <hi>Protestation,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant</hi> are all one; and a clear <hi>Harmony</hi> betwixt all foure, The <hi>Protestation, Covenant, Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacie</hi> and <hi>Allegeance:</hi> And that all these are as contrary to Oxfords Covenant, as <hi>good</hi> is to <hi>evill;</hi> which fully cleareth, That the Lords of the world, <hi>Keepers</hi> of the <hi>Seals</hi> and Souls there, are such <hi>keepers,</hi> as <hi>Cain</hi> was of his Brother. This Epistle to the Reader contains the summe of the Answer.</head>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader; for thy sake, and better information, who art not wilfully blind (i. e. not <hi>willingly ignorant</hi>) I will presume very far, To enquire into the <hi>Covenant,</hi> entred into lately by the <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and charged upon the whole Land. This carries the face of <hi>Presumption,</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> both together. Of folly, To <hi>take a Vow,</hi> and <hi>afterwards enquire:</hi> Of Presumption, To enquire into the Justice of that, which the Nobles and Worthies, so many wise, so many learned, all the faithfull and truly Godly in that Court, have resolved upon, To be agreeable in every point and circumstance therein, with the sacred Rule: the practise also of all the excellent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in the world, upward to this day. But, Pardon me, Reader, as the <hi>King</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will, and all His good people on earth: for I can say heartily, when I heard of this <hi>Vow,</hi> (which I did before I saw it) I concluded presently, That it was as the Commandment, <hi>holy, just,</hi> and <hi>good;</hi> yet I would <hi>enquire</hi> into it, ponder it well, before I took it; And so I did: And so I quit my self of <hi>folly.</hi> So shall I of <hi>presumption</hi> too; Because, I hear this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant (sacred though it be) Preached against by some, a <hi>Bishop</hi> at large, and a <hi>Bishop would be:</hi> Contradicted by others, who know not what they say; Blasphemed by others, who care not what they say, having sold themselves to do wickedly. All this was expected; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, That they, who make no Conscience of their Duty, would make as little of a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and teach their Disciples so; expected, That <hi>Leichfeilds</hi> Presse should Print Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; for if there are mouthes open that way (as there be very many) these are in Oxford good store; and, if <hi>Hell</hi> be above ground, and the Divels any where incarnate cloathed with flesh, there they be. Truly I am glad that <hi>Leichfeilds</hi> Presse, has such a large Licence; (though I wish they had a better Oratour, and the Presse a more able Corrector) for my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is (I will not call it a Conceit) That the more visible the Divell is, and his workmen are, and the more legible their works, the more we shall hate him, and them, and abhorre their works. Now I shall tell thee my undertaking here for thy Profit; To set the Covenant clear,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159067:4"/> That it is agreeable to the sacred Rule in every part and parcell thereof; there I shall shew (in passage) That the Protestation and Covenant are all one, And that Oxford Covenant is abominable; I shall be very brief where there is nothing whereat the tender Conscience can strain at; There we shall run apace, yet so as I may not out-run my Readers understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. When this is done, I shall briefly shew, That there is nothing in the <hi>Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie</hi> and <hi>Allegeance,</hi> which crosseth the Covenant now. In the last place, I shall answer the five <hi>Observations</hi> (sent from <hi>Leichfeilds</hi> Presse in Oxford) upon the late <hi>Covenant,</hi> and set down as many <hi>Castigations</hi> upon <hi>Oxford Covenant, tendred to all the Kings Subjects;</hi> then I shall put <hi>2.</hi> Cases. And I verily beleeve, when this is done, I shall choake the Presse there, and render the said <hi>Covenant,</hi> as indeed it is, as his pernicious Councell hath framed it, so odious and abominable, That no honest man in the world, but will rather suffer himself to be <hi>cut in sunder,</hi> then take it. I have given thee an Account (Reader) of my under taking; now <hi>God</hi> speed us both, Me in what I write; Thee in what thou Readest: then we shall see more then Reason, why we should take the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>stand</hi> unto it; for it shall appear now to be according to the exactest Rule, The good <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> It begins;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <p>I <hi>A. B. In humility and Reverence of the Divine Majesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It begins very well; In humbling the soul before <hi>God,</hi> which cannot be, before His <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy makes us afraid, and His dread fall upon us</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Job 13.11.</note>. When we set <hi>God</hi> before us on His Throne; and draw-out His Attributes, Then we fall low; Then we are <hi>vile,</hi> and He is exalted; <hi>I have heard of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hee by the hearing of the Eare, now mine Eye seeth Thee</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Job 42.45.</note>. What then? <hi>Therefore I abhorre my self, and R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pent in dust and ashes.</hi> See the nineth Chapters, of <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah, Daniel.</hi> Read everywhere; where you see the Servants of the <hi>Lord</hi> entring upon such a businesse as this is, more closly drawing-up their Spirits to, and entring Covenant with their <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declare my hearty sorrow:</hi> This is sacred Scripture sure. <hi>I have declared my sins as Sodome</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Isa. 3 9.</note>, I must now declare my hearty sorrow. If I have any <hi>ornaments, I must put them off from me</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 33.5. Every dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple thought himself the <hi>Judas.</hi>
                  </note> I must <hi>declare</hi> my <hi>hearty sorrow,</hi> the affliction of soul, for the sin of my soul; <hi>[for my own sins]</hi> The Disciples heard their Master speaking of treasonable thoughts against Him; then every one laid their hand on their heart, and, being <hi>exceed ng sorrowfull</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Matth. 26 22.</note>, they said, <hi>Lord, is it I?</hi> (it contains much). <hi>David</hi> said, <hi>Is it not I? Even I it is, that have sinned and done evil indeed</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">1 Chron. 21.17.</note>: but, as for <hi>these sheep what have they done? Let thy hand,</hi> &amp;c and so forth, for it is very notable, but we proceed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the sinnes of this Nation, which have deserved the Calamities and Iudgements that now lie upon it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the heart is truly afflicted for its own sins, when a man can say, I am <hi>indeed justly in this condemnation</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 23.40. Nehe. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.7.</note>; when he can read his own heart, he can read the sinnes of the Nation in that little map, <hi>We have sinned against Thee, both I and my fathers house</hi> have sinned; we have dealt very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly, our Princes, our Nobles, all degrees, all estates, in an unanswerablenesse to all our relations, (it is legible every where) <hi>Iudah</hi> is distressed, because of their <hi>idolatries,</hi> and <hi>bloodshed,</hi> and the <hi>Lord hath not spared.</hi> The confessions of the godly in all Ages have been free and full this way; They have sate down astonished confessing thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>contrary walking,</hi> and, in humble <hi>acceptance</hi> of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment. The Churches Lamentations are full this way, and their Prayers every where.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And my true intention is, by</hi> Gods <hi>grace, to endeavour the amendment of my own wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, else all that went before is vain; serves but to increase sin, guilt, and the punishment. <hi>Surely it is meet to be said unto God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 34.31. Deut. 13. Josh 24.19.23, 24, 25 Act. 11.23</note>
                  <hi>I have born chastisement, I will not offend any more.</hi> Do I enter into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with <hi>God?</hi> Have I gained upon my <hi>will</hi> so farre? Then I must resolve to cast away my Idols, strange <hi>gods,</hi> lying vanities, every thing which will <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ust</hi> me away from <hi>God,</hi> for I have chosen the <hi>Lord, To serve Him, even I and my house.</hi> This is a clear command from the <hi>Word,</hi> Therefore agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto; that, with <hi>full purpose of heart</hi> we should <hi>amend our wayes</hi> and <hi>cleave unto</hi> God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>"And that I do abhor and detest the said wicked and treacherous designe lately discovered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I must digresse a little, yet not from my scope; It is known to every man, who is not willingly blind that Covenants may be renued, as Mercies or Deliverances are renued; These may be made as often
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159067:4"/> as Discoveries of <hi>Gods</hi> hand for His people; or of mens hearts against His People are made manifest. So also as <hi>God</hi> comes neer to a people in His wrath, and sore judgements, so to come up neerer and closer unto Him in Covenant, is commendable, yea commanded evermore: and evermore hath been the practise of <hi>Gods</hi> people. And as we find our hearts fleeting, and started away from Him, so to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call them again, and put them under faster bands, thereby to engage our selves more unto <hi>God.</hi> This, I say, is a cleared Truth. I speak of it here, Because it is said, The Nobles and Commons entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Protestation two yeers ago. Yes, they did so; I do not know how they did it, I know how I did it, slackly enough; but they and we did it. What then? May not they, that took a <hi>Protestation</hi> then, enter into a Covenant now? Yes, certainly, and upon as inforcing Reasons (if it could be, I would say, more inforcing now, then then). Then there were mightie Adversaries risen-up against the <hi>Lord</hi> to thrust His people from Him, and His service, Bidding them go and serve other gods. No not they, they would die first; the more they were pressed, the neerer and closer they came-up to their <hi>God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Josh. 24.</note> they Protested to take Him for their <hi>God; To hear Him, follow Him, serve Him;</hi> He is our <hi>God.</hi> We Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tested <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o take Him for our <hi>God,</hi> to follow none other, but as they follow Christ, and lead unto Him: To be commanded by none other, but as they command from His mouth; for <hi>He is given a Leader, and Commander to His people.</hi> And so we protested to maintain the worship and service of our <hi>God,</hi> against the Divell and all his sworn servants, the Pope and all his Bishops. And whereas there was an Invasion upon the very Crown of the Kingdom, they protested to maintain the Regall Authoritie, the <hi>higher Power,</hi> and the <hi>Rights</hi> belonging thereunto, with their hearts and with their hands. And last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when the Adversary, mightie to oppresse, had indeavoured, and laid hands on the Kingdomes <hi>Birthright,</hi> their Rights and just Liberties; they vowed (and they will not repent) to oppose these Adversaries to the death; Be they Bishops, or Lawyers, or Divels (he is their Prince) they will oppose these to the death, for they are a free people, and so they will die, so runs the <hi>Protestation</hi> even into these heads; Now they enter into <hi>Covenant.</hi> These twaine are one. But I am to shew here, that, as the neerer <hi>God</hi> comes towards us in judgement, the closer His people ought to come-up to Him in Covenant: So also, when <hi>God</hi> shall discover His hand, His Right-hand for His people; And the hearts of His Adversaries against them, then ought His people also to enter into Covenant with their <hi>God,</hi> to stand faster to Him, and His Cause, I meane, (they ought) with more spirit and life, contend for <hi>God,</hi> His Gospel, the more; the more they find it opposed and contended against, as it is at this day. When God has discovered, laid open to the world a work of Darknesse (indeed I know not what to call it, a Hellish Plot, for the Divell had his hand in it, and all his <hi>Right</hi> men) the utter destruction (upon designe) of a Mother City, to be <hi>destroyed,</hi> to be <hi>slain,</hi> and <hi>to perish.</hi> Oh horrible! Yes,<note place="margin">Esth. 7.</note> but that is not all, though the <hi>Enemie could not countervail the Kings Damage in this,</hi> the designe was what ever the pretence was (hear what they say of it, who were appointed to die, that) the designe was, to take away all that is dear and precious to the people either in Earth or Heaven. I know the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie cannot take away <hi>God</hi> from a people, nor Heaven out of their eye; No their eyes are to Heaven, more <hi>stedfastly</hi> fixed thitherward, the more mad the Adversary is with rage against them: But this was upon designe, to take away all (to their power in their hands over <hi>Gods</hi> people) Earth and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and all; when <hi>God</hi> now had made all this clear as the Sun; the Nobles and Worthies call a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, Resolve upon the question, to enter into Covenant, and enjoyn all the Land thereunto, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor and detest the said designe; Every man to wash his hand and heart of it, to do his utmost to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the like intendment in after times. And this <hi>I vow heartily,</hi> and upon as good warrant as <hi>Pauls</hi> Sisters sonne had, to discover these cursed Murtherers, who had bound themselves with a <hi>curse,</hi> that <hi>they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 23.12</note>
               </p>
               <p>Wee proceed. <hi>And whereas I do in my Conscience Beleeve, That the forces Raised by the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of Parliament, are raised and Continued for their Iust Defence, and for the defence of the true Protestant Religion, and Libertie of the Subject, against the forces Raised by the King, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here tender Consciences do Check, theirs I meane, <hi>who strain at a gnat, and swallow a Cammel;</hi> make no Conscience of holding two or three places; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y can gather their Easter-Book, and Tyth's from them all, and then their work is don; They have the fleece, let the Devill and his <hi>grievous</hi> Wolves take and destroy the flocke; Their Consciences make no check there: But at the Covenant th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y straine, and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne their People so; one Minister, and but one that has the outside of holinesse, hath preached against the Covenant; he is a <hi>nov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce,</hi> and I heare he has repented, there is good cause why he should, even open his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outh in Confession before his <hi>God;</hi> for he has opened the mouth of the Adversary to blaspheme: wo unto those Ministers that have done so, for like Priest, like People. <hi>Reader,</hi> mark these fellowes, that oppose the Covenant; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y may be <hi>Divines</hi> (so they will be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d) and <hi>Lawyers</hi> also, but make no question of this, That there are as good and conscionable Men as either of both in <hi>Newgate;</hi> They will lye and couzen, and sweare falsly, holding fast unjust gaines,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159067:5"/> and do yet more wickedly, and no offence to Conscience in all this. But to enter into Covenant, there is an offence. And yet they are not against entering into Covenant, so it be <hi>Oxford</hi> Covenant; That is to their hearts, they can take it, and yet not scruple their Consciences at all. And very good Reason why? Because they, who have framed that Covenant, are as themselves, <hi>Ʋngodly men, walking after their ungodly lusts, Sensuall, having not the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Oxford Covenant examined how sacred it is.</note>I will now for the <hi>Readers</hi> Information examine only the <hi>structure</hi> of <hi>Oxfords</hi> Covenant, what Bottom it has; Thus he Read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that takes it:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I, Resting fully assured of his Majesties Princely truth and goodnesse, do freely and from my heart Promise, Vow, and Protest▪</hi> What to do? <hi>To maintain the True Protestant Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not by Profession a Divine, or Lawyer, yet I am confident, this is not good <hi>Divinitie,</hi> nor <hi>Law</hi> neither; That I should Rest so assured of a Mans <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>goodnesse,</hi> (I will speake of him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that generall Notion) as That I may thereon ground and Bottom, so sacred a Promise, Vow, and Protestation. Man is a creature full of Changes; he has a heart <hi>desperately wicked;</hi> he that had yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day some shewes of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>goodnesse,</hi> may be to day so drawne aside by his owne <hi>will,</hi> so affianced, nay married to his own Lusts, that there is no appearance in him at all of any <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>goodnesse.</hi> Therefore a mans <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>goodnesse</hi> is no bottom for mee, whereon to ground such a <hi>structure,</hi> as the <hi>Divines</hi> and <hi>Lawyers</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> have framed. So sure as wee live, so sure it is against sound <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> both. And me thinkes it is no good <hi>Logick</hi> neither, and that is sound <hi>Reason,</hi> which assureth mee, That, whether there be truth and goodnesse in the Ruler, or none at all, yet I stand bound to the uttermost of my Power, To <hi>maintaine the Protestant Religion.</hi> This is enough to shew, The <hi>Bottom</hi> is naught; They make mention of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Israel,</hi> but not in <hi>Truth, in Iudgement,</hi> nor <hi>in Righteousnesse.</hi> But now the Kings <hi>loyall Subjects</hi> have taken this <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant.</hi> Who have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it? All the Kings Army, and they are <hi>Papists</hi> every man. You must be so charitable as to beleeve it, for one of their own tells us so much, he that sent us a Copy of their Covenant, he (I thinke before he was aware) tells us so, in his second <hi>Observation,</hi> which I will observe, I warrant him, when I come to it. I was making a question a little before, how these sworn-men Performe their <hi>Vow,</hi> their sacred Vow and Covenant? It is Answered, <hi>To the utmost of their Power,</hi> so they will <hi>maintaine the true Protestant Religion, his Majesties Sacred Person, the just Power and Priviledges of King and Parliament, against the forces,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And will not take, nor beare Armes, but by the expresse and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Warrant of his Majesty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Looke you here with halfe an Eye, for that will serve the turne, To find out the most illegall Oath, that ever was taken, for he sweares it lawfull for a King, by his immediate Warrant, to <hi>Aray</hi> three Kingdomes <hi>(i. e.)</hi> To call forth All his People to war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. If this be good Law, then wee know not what is good Reason. But though there be neither <hi>Law</hi> nor Reason in their <hi>Covenant,</hi> yet may this Legion of Papists (that is graunted) Evidence both, That they are loyall Subjects, and Reasonable Men, in their legal Prosecution thereof; for the <hi>Defence of the True Protestant Religion, his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Sacred Person, Just Power and Priviledges of Parliament.</hi> Where is their Evidence, that they have kept Covenant? That is <hi>declared</hi> to all the world, a yeare since, and now very lately, what they have d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in <hi>Ireland;</hi> Besides the Evidence is very cleare here also, for wee may reade it written very legible, as their Lawes are, in most Bloudy Characters. Let them sweare, wee will pray; <q rend="margDblQuotes">Into their secret let my soul never come:<note place="margin">Gen. 47.6, 7.</note> unto their Assembly mine honour be not thou united; <hi>for</hi> in their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they have slaine men, and in their selfe-will they have Thrust sore at three Kingdomes. Cursed be their Anger, for it was fierce, and their wrath for it was cruell: Lord divide them in Iacob, and scatter them in Israel, Amen. <hi>O do not Deliver-up thy Turtle Dove, thy owne People, thy owne truth, into the hands of such</hi> Defenders, <hi>not the sheep of thy Pasture unto grievous Wolves, Amen, and Amen.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And now Reader, having given thee a <hi>taste</hi> of Oxfords Covenant, (I have but dipped my pen in it) I am very confident, wee shall <hi>Relish</hi> ours the better; wee can now with more clearnesse of Judgement, <q rend="margDblQuotes">Proceed, every Man saying, <hi>In my Conscience I beleeve.</hi> That the forces raised by the King &amp; Queen, are raised purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly to destroy (to their Power in their hand) the true Religion, Just Power and Priviledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of King and Parliament:</q> And that the forces raised by the Parliament, are <hi>Raised</hi> and <hi>Continued</hi> for the just defence of all the fore-mentioned, in Defiance of, and against all the Devils in Hell, and his Subjects on Earth, now giving forth their hands and hearts to the King and Queene, for the Destruction of three Kingdoms at once. In conscience and full beliefe hereof, I do here <hi>in the presence of Almightie God,</hi> Declare, Vow, and Covenant, to assist the Parliaments forces, according to my Power, and Vocation, Raised and continued in defence of themselves, the true Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Liberties of the Subject. And according to the utmost of my Power, and in my Place, I will call in all to <hi>assist, associate,</hi> and <hi>knit themselves together,</hi> as <hi>one</hi> man, in pursuance of this Designe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159067:5"/> for <hi>Defence of them,</hi> whom wee have Chosen to stand up for us; and who have engaged themselves in the breach; In <hi>Defence of them,</hi> who have layd-out themselves for us, with the expence of Time, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and Estates. <hi>God</hi> be thanked, wee are not so bruitish, so forsaken of our witts, or common light, to make choice of Men, to Defend us, our Religion, our Liberties, and then to leave these Men to the rage and fury of these <hi>oppressors</hi> so bloudy-men. In truth, to Desert a <hi>Parliament,</hi> were a dealing with the <hi>Politick Body,</hi> head and members all, as the Adversary once dealt with <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Mysticall Head;</hi> He had taught th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, spent Himselfe that way, and in requitall, they carry him to <hi>Edge-Hill,</hi> the very <hi>brow</hi> there, to breake His neck downe from thence. God has added more Grace, Praised be his Name, Wee are a <hi>Willing People,</hi> for the Defence of all the forementioned; Wee solemnly vow, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to gather and <hi>knit our selves together,</hi> All <hi>as one Man,</hi> so to expose our Bodies to be trodden upon, as mire in the streets, before the foot of Pride shall prevaile over our Worthies, destroy the true Religion, and enthrall a free People. This is our Vow and Covenant; And wee solemnly call God to witnesse, <hi>The Almighty God,</hi> ever <hi>present</hi> to assist His friends, and to confound His Adversaries; <hi>The searcher of all hearts,</hi> knows the hearts, thoughts, purposes, intentions there; Wee will deale clearely with Him. To performe my Vow and Covenant fully according to the matter and manner of the same, <hi>as I shall answer at the great Day,</hi> when my body and soule must appeare: my heart must appeare also; all visible there, words, deeds, thoughts, <hi>all secrets shall be Disclosed:</hi> As I looke, that <hi>God</hi> would be mercifull to mee at this Great Day; so have I vowed and covenanted with Him in this day, for the Defence of King, Parliament, Religion, Liberties, as at this day, So help me God. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So far for Explication and Information, now heare what is objected.</p>
               <p>But what have wee don now? Wee have forsworne our selves; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> wee have sworne obedience to the King, the Supreame Power. Now wee vow and sweare cleane crosse to our Oath of <hi>Supremacy, Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> also, sayes the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Lawyer</hi> both.</p>
               <p>These are—wee know what, not such fooles as to beleeve, what themselves say: wee have sworne, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label> and wee verily beleeve what wee swore, That the King, ruling by Law, is the <hi>Supreame Power:</hi> and so wee have sworne Obedience to him: Wee abjure any forraigne Power, wee have sworne, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pope, nor Cardinall, nor the most <hi>Catholick</hi> King, nor the most <hi>Christian</hi> (as they stile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves) shall over-rule our King, or Kingdome, if wee can helpe it. Wee have sworne, and wee doe not repent, for in pursuance of this Oath, to repell forraigne Power, wee are in Armes at this day. We have taken the Oath of <hi>Supremacy:</hi> I pray you peruse it well; A good Man, and a good Lawyer <hi>(Nobile par)</hi> has fitted it to our hands, and the <hi>Oath of Allegeance</hi> too. Wee have sworne Allegeance. To whom? To God, and to the King, in reference to Him. And this I thinke verily the Adversaries will grant, unlesse the Devill be in them. Let them sweare, and curse, and blaspheme, and <hi>Damne</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, yet shall they never sweare themselves <hi>into</hi> this <hi>Oath,</hi> nor sweare us <hi>out</hi> of the same. Wee have sworn, and will not repent; to obey the King, while he obeyes God, ruling his People by his <hi>Law-booke;</hi> Wee have not sworne our selves servants to men, to their private wills, to their lusts, &amp;c. Wee have taken the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and of <hi>Allegeance,</hi> and by the grace of God, wee shall stand unto both to the death; Wee will maintaine the King, the <hi>higher Power,</hi> with our lives and fortunes, wee will obey all his (<hi>Lawfull</hi> not his personall) Commands. Looke into these Oaths, they are presented to your eye, you shall not find a word there soberly understood, contradicting this <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Covenant.</hi> God forbid, that wee should vow our selves servants to men, and rebells to God, God forbid. Reader, I must breake off here, else I should not only manifest the Kings Army to be perjured persons all, the most notorious Covenant-breakers, that ever were in the world; but also, I should give cleare notice, that the Queene, and King (I name her first not for honour sake) are notoriously faulty touching both these Oaths; the one doing her utmost to bring in and establish a forraigne Power; the other denying Allegeance to the <hi>most Supreme.</hi> I have don.</p>
               <p>"But where have you any warrant to take up <hi>Armes</hi> against the King? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obs. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Wee will never allow those words <hi>against the King,</hi> they are taken up for the King, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label> for the defence of him, and all that should be dearest to him. But let it goe, <hi>Against the King;</hi> wee have warrant for it, when he bends his force, all his might, sets open the gates of hell against the Parliament, against Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion, against our Lawes, &amp;c. Wee vow and covenant now, to take-up Armes now against King, Queene, both (for shee is more masculine at this worke) setting themselves against God, and the power of godlinesse. And wee have as good warrant, [which I will bring forth anon,] as can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired for so doing.</p>
               <p>I must first contend with an Adversary, who having the Universitie licence, to speake from <hi>Leich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lds</hi> Presse in Oxford, <hi>boasteth great things.</hi> Truly I had almost called him <hi>knave</hi> at the first dash; And well he deserves it, for he calls the <hi>Parliament</hi> of England <hi>Malignants</hi> all, at the very first word.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159067:6"/> But though he deserves that name, and more, a Rope to boot, yet I thinke better of my selfe, and of my rule,<note place="margin">Jude 9.</note> then to returne railing words, though I were to contend with the Devill, and with him, surely, I must contend now, for without controversie, the Devill is the <hi>Bishop of Oxford,</hi> now <hi>Chiefe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seer</hi> of all the affaires don there, the great <hi>Mannager,</hi> by his under-officers, of all busines concerning the state, and the Popes Kingdome, and has supplied <hi>Leichfeilds</hi> Presse with worke good store, ever since the Kings <hi>Councell</hi> came thither. Therefore I cannot doubt neither, but if I can answer this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary, (as I doubt not but I shall,) I shall silence the Devill; And yet I would not have <hi>Leichfeilds</hi> Presse stand still; I speake from my heart, I thinke he do's God service against his will; he Prints such horrible lies, and blasphemies, that Gods servants, are the more in love with truth: And sending us up their Covenant last weeke, with some Clerke-like <hi>Observations</hi> upon ours, he has rendered their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant more horrid and formidable, and ours more desireable and gracious. Truly when I take a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to Oxford, which with my will, will not be yet, I may thanke <hi>Leichfeild</hi> for all this; and shall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to procure a Check to the Lord Keeper, even from his King, whom he has notoriously abused by his carelesse oversight of the Covenant there, which I presume passed his hand, as the <hi>Proclamations</hi> doe, yet do's he suffer men to vow and covenant, that they will beare or not beare Armes at the <hi>sole Command and immediate Warrant of their King;</hi> whom they have stollen from his <hi>Court,</hi> even the high Court of Parliament; and left alone to rule by his owne <hi>Will,</hi> whereto, notwithstanding, the Keeper, sweares Allegeance. Indeed he will be blamed for that, for he knows it is against Law and all good reason: A grand exception against the <hi>legality</hi> of that Covenant. Now heare what the <hi>Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> sayes touching ours.</p>
               <p>His Preface contains very bad language, and very little Reason, but it came from Oxford; I passe it over, noting onely, before I come to his Observations, that he saies, <hi>These two Covenants tendred now to the Kingdome are contrary.</hi> Indeed they are, I could have told him so much; the Parliaments Vow and Covenant is as contrary to Oxfords Vow and Covenant, as Light is to Darknesse: Heaven is to Hell. Look through the whole structure, and composition, the matter and manner of both, how they begin, proceed, how they end. It were worth the going over by peeces again, but it cannot be. There are the most notorious contradictions in Oxfords Covenant, that ever were read. <hi>God</hi> forbid there should be a letter sounding that way, in this we have taken. But in Oxfords Covenant, besides the <hi>illegalitie</hi> and unreasonablenesse of it, there are the most manifest contradictions, that are ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineable. No such contradiction as when the hand contradicts the tongue, the <hi>Practise</hi> goes against conscience,<note place="margin">Math. 21.28.</note> that is a notorious contradiction. What think you? saies our <hi>Saviour Christ:</hi>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">A certaine man had two sonnes; he said to the first, Son, go work to day in my vineyard. <hi>He answered and said,</hi> I will not.</q> There was a contradiction from the tongue. But afterwards he repented and went. To the second the Father said likewise; the Sonne answered, <hi>I go sir,</hi> and went not. There was a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the hand, or heart, or life, take which you please. A notorious Hypocrite, he made shewes and semblances of doing his Fathers will; <hi>I will sir:</hi> but it was in his heart to do contrary. Our <hi>Lord</hi> puts a question upon this, <hi>Whether of the twain did the will of his Father?</hi> Not he, that said well, but he that did well: Not he, that was contrary in his word, but he that was contrary in his deed. Verily saies the <hi>Lord Christ,</hi> the most notorious sinners that ever were upon the face of the Earth will go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdom of <hi>God</hi> before this man. What man? That Sonne, who made a semblance, gave a fair promise (though he did not vow) of obedience <hi>(I go sir)</hi> yet went not. <hi>Publicans and Harlots go into the Kingdom of God before this man.</hi> I ask the same question. What think you, of all them, who have taken Oxfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Covenant? Good men all, you will say, for they promise faire, and vow too, so they are and <hi>are</hi> before the wicked sonne in the Gospel: But the most notorious sinners, that ever were, shall go before them into the kingdom of <hi>God.</hi> Because they promise and vow, and do not; they contradict with the hand, what they said and vowed with the mouth. They said they <hi>will</hi> maintaine the true Religion, the Kings sacred person, his and the Parliaments just power and priviledges. <hi>I go sir,</hi> so every man for his part, hath promised and vowed. Have they done it? Yes, the clean contrary way, to the uttermost of their power, to destroy Religion, King, Kingdom, witnesse their <hi>open force</hi> and <hi>secret treacheries;</hi> I was about to say more, but more needs not, all the Christian world is satisfied, we need not farther witnesse.</p>
               <p>We examine now the harmony and sweet agreement betwixt the tongue, and hand in the other Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. The <hi>Lord Christ</hi> hath charged upon the Parliament the <hi>care</hi> and <hi>cure</hi> of three Kingdoms. <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>Go</hi> for Me, do for Me, lay out your selves for Me, Who gave my Self for you; contend against the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ones, for the Faith once given to My Saints; Stand-up in the breach for Me, Who stood alone in the Wine-press<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of My Fathers wrath for you (a reasonall request);</q> They answered every man apart, and said, <hi>(I will sir)</hi> I promise and vow and enter into Covenant, nay into a curse, <hi>I will sir,</hi> and I will do as I say, maintain the true Religion, contend for the faith, &amp;c. I appeal now to all the Christian
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159067:6"/> world, nay to Heaven too, God, Angels, and men, have they not done it, to the uttermost of their power, and beyond it? Blessed be <hi>God</hi> that so they have done. And this is their rejoycing in this day of Rebuke, and Blasphemie, that, so they have done; their hand hath not given their tongue the lie. And now should there follow a great <hi>Earthquake, such as was not since men were upon the Earth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 16.18.</note>
                  <hi>so mighty an Earthquake and so great,</hi> (which may well be, now that the cursed <hi>Hierarchy</hi> (which hath taken such deep Root, and cumbred the ground so long, must be rooted-up) if so, yet can they hold fast to their <hi>God,</hi> they can rejoyce in Him, the <hi>God</hi> of their <hi>salvation.</hi> What? tell them who are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with their God, (and by His strength will stand to it) tell them, things go ill in the <hi>North,</hi> and in the <hi>West.</hi> They will tell you, things go well; for <hi>God</hi> will have it so, He will bring His ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the mount, but He will <hi>appeare in His glory</hi> there. Tell them, that men are unfaithfull, and treacherous: they can tell you so, and more; that <hi>David</hi> said, <hi>All men are lyars;</hi> and for their part, they never put confidence in men, no not in themselves, they trust God, they did their work (that is their duty) and commended the rest to <hi>God,</hi> Who is faithfull. They hold fast their confidence, that, if all their <hi>party</hi> were <hi>wounded men,</hi> yet this <hi>Cause</hi> must overcome; It is not theirs, but <hi>Gods;</hi> and the Cause never offended God, though His servants have offended Him, perhaps, in the managing of a good Cause, yet, they say, the Cause is <hi>Gods,</hi> the <hi>managers</hi> of it, are Gods people. What then? Then God will maintain His cause, and pardon His servants, that He will; and His servants are as confident of it, as they are, that their <hi>Lord Christ</hi> was upon the Earth once, is now in Heaven, <hi>standing,</hi> I say, <hi>standing</hi> now at <hi>Gods Right-hand, an Advocate with the Father</hi> there.<note place="margin">Psal. 50.</note>
                  <hi>Gather My Saints together unto Me, those that have made a Covenant with Me.</hi> But now this Oxford Scholar tels us, he has more <hi>circumspectly looked</hi> into this Covenant then, haply, others have done; and, to help his simple Reader, he hath set down five <hi>Observations</hi> upon the <hi>Covenant,</hi> as he cals them: what they are you shall read presently, and not a word there, but according to expectation, neither <hi>Law</hi> nor <hi>Reason</hi> from Oxford now: nor will you account it strange, that <hi>good</hi> is called <hi>Evill</hi> there, and <hi>Evill good.</hi> You will be the more confirmed touching this <hi>Covenant,</hi> and more abominate that other, because we grant heartily as much as he saies, that there is a full contrariety betwixt them, this stands in a Diemetricall oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition with that as he saies, and we grant, and yet the <hi>Observator</hi> gaines nothing by all his <hi>Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations,</hi> which we will also observe by and by, when I shall have explained his <hi>Tearme</hi> first. He in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigheth very much against a <hi>Malignant party.</hi> The honest Reader will be mistaken here quite; for he will understand them to be the party at <hi>Oxford:</hi> and the <hi>Observator</hi> sayes, It is the party here at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> he means the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> they are <hi>malignants</hi> all. Indeed it is a bold word, to call the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England Malignants;</hi> But he may be bold at <hi>Oxford,</hi> having a warrant there under the <hi>Great Seale</hi> (such a <hi>Keeper</hi> it has) not onely to dispite the Parliament, but to fight against them too. This is <hi>Oxfords</hi> dialect right; and but after the old manner, which was to call <hi>others by their own name,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exutem me de suo nomine vocat. Cic. par.</hi> 1 King 18 17. 2 Chron. 23.13. <hi>Obj.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <hi>Malignants.</hi> So <hi>Ahab</hi> the King did anciently, and so did his Queene too, and their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter also; These said that <hi>Elijah,</hi> that good Prophet, was a <hi>malignant,</hi> a troubler of <hi>Israels</hi> Peace, and his head should off, said Queene <hi>Iezabel,</hi> as if it had been as easily don as a calves-head is fetcht from the Market: So was the good Priest too, a <hi>Troubler;</hi> and if the Queene might have had her will, <hi>Jehoja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> had been put to death as a Traitor, but he had the law of her, and slew her. I come now to his obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, he observes,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That in the Covenant composed by this malignant party</hi> (he means the Parliament) <hi>There is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their defence onely;</hi> no <hi>mention of the Kings preservation at all, or maintenance of his just Rights.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having observed so, he frets and fumes, and boyles up to a great <hi>scum,</hi> you may see it coming out at his lips. Indeed there was no cause of all this chafe, for the man is quite mistaken, <hi>Heavenly wide,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Toto Caeli errat.</note> as a proud Prelate said once; he is deceived, whether willingly or ignorantly I cannot tell, but I guesse, he is neither <hi>Lawyer,</hi> nor <hi>Divine,</hi> nor good <hi>Logician</hi> neither: for these will all tell him, That you cannot divide the <hi>Head Politick,</hi> from the <hi>Body Politick.</hi> God has joyned them together, and cursed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he that seperates them, the Parliament does not. The King is with the Parliament; they doe not meane his Personall presence, be that where it <hi>will</hi> be, the King is with his Parliament, his Royall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority there, in his lawes, in his Courts of Justice, in that <hi>high Court,</hi> in a more eminent manner; The head is with the Body, the King with his Parliament, that he is, sayes the <hi>Law, Divinity, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick,</hi> all these three, Reason I meane; Therefore, what ever has been don since first there was a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>England</hi> up-wards to this day, for the defence of the Parliament, Religion, Lawes, Liberties, was don primarily, and chiefly, for the defence of the King, his just Rights, &amp;c. For I could say much more to it, but I am confined, not to a <hi>Circle,</hi> but to a sheet of Paper. Notwithstanding, I must g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve my <hi>Observation</hi> too upon <hi>Oxfords</hi> Covenant, which is this, <hi>That the preservation of the King and Kingdome, His and the Parliaments just Rights and Liberties, from that hellish Designe against King
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159067:7"/> and Kingdome, is not at all mentioned amongst them at</hi> Oxford. Assuredly, the <hi>Living God,</hi> the <hi>Lord God</hi> of gods, has a Controversie with the <hi>Keeper</hi> for this, that he would call the Kings loyall Subjects to enter into Covenant, and never remember them of that deliverance from the mouth of the Lion, and claw of the <hi>She Beare,</hi> That devouring Destruction in Designe against the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and the whole Kingdome, so lately discovered. I know well his Lordship has an Answer for this, That h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mselfe had an hand in it, he sealed a Commission to those Murtherers, thereby giving them a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to shed bloud to their power. But he shall know shortly, what goes for <hi>Law</hi> in the Court at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> will be Treason in the Court of heaven. He observes:</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">That they vow never to lay downe Armes, so long as the Papists now in Armes against the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (as they say) shall be kept from the Justice of it; that is, till the Kings Army be overcome.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Well, said Oxford Schollar! The veriest Malignant in <hi>London</hi> (as they say at Oxford) could not have said more to my purpose; The <hi>Observator</hi> grants, That the Kings Army are Papists all. It will be my observation anon too, that the chiefe part are so, for I shall not carry it so farre, as he does, and conclude as he does, <hi>That all the Kings Army are Papists.</hi> I shall conclude, That the greatest part are Papists, and that the Parliament has warrant from the example of all the <hi>Israel of God,</hi> not to lay downe Armes till the Kings Army be overcome; That is, till the Papists now in Armes against the Parliament, be delivered up to the Justice of it. <q rend="margDblQuotes">But the <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> will be very angry at this Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, I know, though it be pretty Logicall; for, indeed, it is a very shrewd Inference; The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vow never to lay downe Armes, so long as the Papists, now in Armes against the Parliament, shall be kept from the Justice of it <hi>(Ergo)</hi> Therefore they must not lay downe Armes till the Kings Army be overcome.</q> Truly I should not have been so bold as to have concluded so, <hi>That all the Kings Army are Papists;</hi> though to give every one his due, this yong man (I suppose he is a<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Newly matricula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. 1 Tim. 3.6</note>
                  <hi>novice</hi>) hath profited for his time in the University very well, his Parents need not repent of their cost; their <hi>childe</hi> speaks Logick, explaines his termes reasonably, his Inference is very rationall too: yet I know it is not good <hi>Logick</hi> in <hi>Oxford</hi> at this time; and the Lord Keeper will be angry at it; We shall read more of this anon, for I shall returne to it againe, and then I shall take into consideration, what he <hi>observes</hi> in the third place, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That the Covenant taken now, is not a Covenant but a Combination: and they that enter into it are Conspirators all.</q> You shall heare more touching the second and third observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both together: he observes;</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label>
                  <hi>That the Parliaments Covenant is to be constrained,</hi> and <hi>that the Kings Covenant is voluntary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label> They appeale to God in this, that the contrary is truth. The Parliament will <hi>force</hi> it upon no man: And yet they may disarme those that will not take the Covenant, and leave such so naked, that they shall not be able to make any <hi>force</hi> or <hi>head</hi> against the Parliament, which such persons are too ready to doe: And if the Parliament shall wholly disable these Malignants from making resistance, and <hi>forcing</hi> them, they have all the Laws in heaven and earth to warrant them in so doing. The <hi>Observator</hi> must say contrary to this, <hi>That the Kings Covenant is voluntary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know not how they deale in this, I know that the <hi>Vow</hi> or <hi>Protestation,</hi> (I know not what it was, but an <hi>unrighteous Decree</hi> it was,<note place="margin">Isa. 10 1.</note> there they did <hi>prescribe grievousnesse,</hi> and <hi>woe unto them saith the Lord</hi>) hath been so pressed, upon both <hi>free</hi> and <hi>bond-men</hi> there, since the Kings Councell sate at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> that they who had their eyes and consciences open, and could not take it, were (besides most barbarous and never before this day heard-of cruelties by men executed upon men) suffered to dye for thirst. So their tongues were dried like an <hi>hearth;</hi> and their tyred breath was <hi>forced</hi> out of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; Why? Because they would not suffer their Consciences to be <hi>forced</hi> that way: <hi>God</hi> hath looked upon this, and will require it. My observation here is cleane contrary to the <hi>Observators, That the Parliaments Covenant is voluntary: the Kings</hi> (the former and this now) <hi>constrained.</hi> If that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hath <hi>forced</hi> the soule out of the body, this now will doe more, force the Conscience too, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the soule: He observes fifthly,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>5</label>
                  <hi>That the Parliament entered into Covenant first.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label> It was well they did, and what if they did? Then he will make this <hi>use thereof,</hi> (so he saith) <hi>To prove, That theirs is the offensive Warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> I will spare him, for I thinke againe of my example and <hi>Rule</hi> both,<note place="margin">Jude 9.</note> though I have knowne a foole and a knave both, a mad man also (sometimes) speake a great deale more wisely. All the world will grant, that a Parliament may <hi>Protest</hi> to take God for their God, to renue Covenant with their <hi>God,</hi> as we reade before, and yet not be an <hi>offensive</hi> party. What? Because they ought to use all meanes to make Peace with their God; will he make this <hi>use</hi> of it to conclude <hi>(Ergo)</hi> therefore they first made warre with their King? They Protested two yeares agoe, to <hi>serve God,</hi> their King, and Kingdome: They enter into a new Covenant now, binding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves with faster bands, to contend for the <hi>faith,</hi> maintaine their Religion, the <hi>just Rights</hi> of King and Kingdome, against Atheists and Papists, bloudy Adversaries to both, who would make voyd these
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159067:7"/>
                  <hi>just Rights,</hi> lay all waste, making an <hi>Eden</hi> before them, a <hi>Wildernesse</hi> behind them. What use will you make of this? To prove, that the Parliament is the <hi>offended,</hi> the Kings the <hi>offnding party;</hi> wee are agreed; And to make farther use of it also, to prove, that the Gates of Hell, power and policy shall not prevaile against this Parliament; They are in Covenant with their God, they clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to him. But their enemies shall be destroyed all (in Gods time) In the meane time, they are a <hi>broken fence,</hi> and as a <hi>tottering wall.</hi> Thus farre wee are agreed in the use, and farther wee shall agree ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. But now if the <hi>Observator</hi> will make this <hi>use</hi> of it, to prove, that theirs is the <hi>offensive,</hi> the Kings the <hi>Defensive party;</hi> he must prove first, that one Command of <hi>God,</hi> cleane crosseth another <hi>(i. e.)</hi> That when the Parliament fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st and againe made choice <hi>to feare the Lord,</hi> then, at that time, they made choice to dishonour the King; they could not <hi>feare God,</hi> and <hi>honour their King,</hi> both at once; These are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, sayes the <hi>Observator</hi> (in effect) for that is his use, which when he makes, and can make good, I promise him, he shall make me come to <hi>Oxford,</hi> pulling me thither by as small a thread, as is imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, whereas, till he hath made it good, he shall not pull me thither with Cart-ropes. I promise him more, that, having proved as aforesaid, he shall <hi>draw</hi> mee into Covenant with him also, and the rest of his Companions, (though the Tabernacle of Robbers, whom my soule hateth) which now he shall not doe with sixteen yoake of Oxen. And now I will take leave, to make two more short uses for his one, and then I have made three. The first is.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Oxford</hi> is exceedingly to blame, because they should have been the first in Covenant with their <hi>God;</hi> and they were last. There is one use, a use of Reprehension, which truely I could enlarge very usefully (though I know what I shall be accounted for what I have said already) yet it is the very truth; for <hi>Oxford</hi> is [as they know the best Greek-Orator said of one of their Cities] one of the <hi>Eyes</hi> of this Iland; And what is the <hi>use</hi> of an eye, but for direction and guidance of the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> both? What a horrible thing it is, these are last <hi>in Covenant,</hi> who should have been first; certainly the light that is in <hi>Oxford</hi> now is darknesse, and how great is that darknesse? And they are an offence to God, and all goodnesse, and how great is that offence? I cannot expresse it, let them looke to it; It is our first use, <hi>viz.</hi> To prove, that <hi>Oxford</hi> should have been the first in Covenant, or if not so, yet they should have been with the formost; The King and all his loyall Subjects should have entered Covenant together.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I make this <hi>use</hi> of it, <hi>To prove,</hi> that <hi>Oxford</hi> Covenant is an <hi>abomination,</hi> a <hi>curse,</hi> nay, <hi>Hormah, utter destruction</hi> to them that take it, bodies, soules, and all, and tends to the utter destruction of King and Kingdom. I know I should not be short in this use, but this shall serve to prove it quickly, Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ause the Parliament entered into Covenant first, <hi>To feare God, To serve Him,</hi> to contend for the <hi>Faith,</hi> and publick <hi>Trust</hi> of the Kingdome. This is in short the Contents of their Protestation, and Covenant both. <hi>Oxford</hi> came <hi>last,</hi> but enters into Covenant at last With whom? With the Devill, to serve him. Yes, Reader, I startle at it too, as well as you, yet be assured I weighed my words with both my hands, and heart also, before I spake them, knowing well enough, that they must be weighed in the ballance at <hi>Oxford,</hi> they shall not prove light. I will say it againe, <hi>They have entered into Covenant,</hi> not <hi>in terminis,</hi> to serve the Devill so and so. But, which is as bad, indeed and in truth, by necessary consequence, and deduction, nay intentionally so and so, to serve him, the Devill they meane.</p>
               <p>"Why but they have entered into a Covenant to maintaine Religion; that is a good <hi>Terme.</hi>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, a very good word, for they say as wee reade before, <hi>I goe Sir, I will Sir,</hi> but they <hi>will</hi> not indeed; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <hi>Intentionally,</hi> they enter into Covenant to destroy Religion, the faith and trust of the Kingdome ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly: To maintaine the <hi>Rights,</hi> of King and Kingdome, against all the rights of Heaven and Lawes on Earth. And this is the very intention of their hearts [O horrible] witnesse what they do with their hands. Examine well and see whether their doings do not argue, and make the clearest proofe, that they have entered Covenant with the Devill, <hi>To serve him, To worke for him, To stand up for him,</hi> to <hi>goe</hi> for him, to <hi>will</hi> for him, to do as he does, open his mouth in <hi>Blasphemy</hi> against <hi>God, His Name His Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven:</hi> And to warre, as he does, against the <hi>Lamb,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 12.6. Rev. 9.11.</note> and those that are with him, <hi>Called, Chosen,</hi> and <hi>Faithfull;</hi> and so are, as he is called, <hi>Abaddon, Apollyon,</hi> the one is Hebrew, the other Greeke, in plaine <hi>English</hi> one and the same both, <hi>Destroyers</hi> all: They are in Covenant with him, sworn servants to him. I have now omitted the top, and Bottom of their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, but of that before: onely this I will note, that the <hi>Lord Keeper</hi> must mend the Cop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of his Covenant, it is as fowle almost as his <hi>Proclamations</hi> are; the <hi>beginning</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> are against <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Law, Reason,</hi> and not very good sence neither; And certainly the <hi>living God</hi> hath protested a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, that he is as bad a <hi>Keeper</hi> of the <hi>Seale,</hi> as other <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> are of <hi>Souls,</hi> such <hi>Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> all, as <hi>Cain</hi> was <hi>of his Brother.</hi> I have don with the fifth <hi>Observation,</hi> the use, and proofe the <hi>Observator</hi> makes thereof; The uses also and proofes I have made therefrom, which no true Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor Law neither in <hi>Oxford</hi> shall be able to contradict; for I have a great advantage of the Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159067:8"/> (though as vile in my own eyes as I am in his) <hi>Managing</hi> Truth against him and his falshoods, in sinceritie of heart, how weakly soever: whereas <hi>falshood</hi> will confound the best Schollars in the world, the <hi>managers</hi> and maintainers thereof. I have not don yet; I shall puzzell this <hi>Observator</hi> yet more, and more confound their cursed <hi>Covenant,</hi> now that I can returne to my Adversaries second and third <hi>Observations,</hi> which he hath noted, to set a note of disgrace upon ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, so to darken our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; But it shall cleare it altogether, from the most cleared example (except one) that ever was seene upon earth. And now while the adversaries are fretting, and chafing with themselves, perhaps with their <hi>Observator,</hi> who observed their Covenant so little, and ours so much, while they are muzing about their Covenant, and, perhaps, checking themselves inwardly for what they have don, I will, with Gods helpe, muze upon <hi>Davids</hi> 140. <hi>Psalme,</hi> That encouraging, that establishing <hi>Psalme;</hi> I will muze up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it from the very first words to the last, and then I shall muze upon all the wonderfull works of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which He hath don and will doe for his friends, and against his Adversaries, those cursed <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters.</hi> And the good <hi>Lord</hi> helpe me, and helpe us all, not to leave muzing, till, by the helpe of his Spirit, we have workt up our Spirits so high, as that we can say with the <hi>upright,</hi>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>Wee shall dwell in Thy presence.</hi> And then, though the wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d imagine mischiefe in their heart; continually are they gathered together for warre;<note place="margin">Ver. 2.</note> though they have sharpened their tongues like a Serpent; yet they shall not come neare us, to do us any hurt (if wee be <hi>upright</hi>) they shall not reach Heaven, Gods dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Place, nor any place which is the place of his presence, where he delights to be; there the <hi>upright</hi> are safe enough, from the violence of hands, and strife of tongues; <hi>The vpright shall dwell in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence,</hi> Amen.</q>
               </p>
               <p>I proceed now to the other two Observations, I will set them downe, then give my Castigations upon them, and Observations from them: I shall propose two cases also, then you shall see how high an account the word of <hi>God</hi> makes of them, and all good men: He observes,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">That the Parliament vow never to lay down Armes so long as the Papists now in Armes against the Parliament (as they say) shall be kept from the Justice of it, that is, till the Kings Army bee overcome.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label> Well, they have said so indeed, and vowed it too, not to lay down Armes, till all the Kings army be overcome; If he can prove his conclusion, which a Logician seldome troubles himself about, his mind is upon the truth of the premises, then the conclusion will follow. But, I say, this being granted, that all the Kings Army are Papists (he has observed it) <hi>(i. e.) Incendiaries, Achans, Troublers,</hi> Pests, Plagues in a Kingdom, winch the Parliament does not say; they do not lay this reproach upon all the Kings Army. But grant it so to be (it is granted at Oxford, and why should we stick at it?) Then they must make good what they said, for their vows are upon them, not lay down Arms, <hi>till the Kings Army he overcome.</hi> So the Observator sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and so the Parliament have vowed, if his Observation be true. Truly I am glad this was printed at Oxford; very glad, that the Scholars there take notice of this Vow; though yet the Adversary has made farther Observation upon it, he observes, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That it is the most irreligious and inhumane Vow that can be imagined (Why?) For it excludes all hopes of commodation and Peace by Treaty </q>[My Observation follows, that, they cannot have such a <hi>fine</hi> Designe upon London again, as they might have had by Treatie, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> by shews and semblances of Peace, when warre is in the heart] He proceeds in his Observation, <q rend="margDblQuotes">and it evidently sheweth, that the setling of Religion, Laws, and Liberties is not the thing the Parliament aymes at</q> [What is his Reason for that? a strange one if it had not come from Oxford] <q rend="margDblQuotes">for the Kings party are sworn by their Covenant (mark it) that that shall be their first endeavour, what?</q> If they make way to London and enter in there, (which <hi>God</hi> forbid, but His will be done, the security of his people is not in wals and barres) <q rend="margDblQuotes">Their prime and chief work shall be to defend the Parliament (the Malignants there) the true Religion, Laws and Liberties.</q> In spight of the Divell I will laugh now sure, for the Divell cries, and is very wrath, Because his Sonnes would make him appeare as an Angel of Light, when as it pleases him best now, to appear as he is, and as his servants are, who are as their names are, <hi>Abaddon Apollyor, Destroyers</hi> all. These semblances of his children makes their Father crie, and roare too: therefore I will laugh; for I am sure God laughs at this, and all His faithfull servants in the world, when they hear it said. <q rend="margDblQuotes">That the Kings party are sworn by their Covenant, That when power is in their hand, the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enance of Religion, Laws, and Liberties of the Subject, shall be their first en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour.</q> The Observator urgeth it again, <q rend="margDblQuotes">That the Parliament did not take up Armes, for the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of the Protestant Rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gion, no, for then, they would have laid them down again upon the Kings Oath, and promise to be as forward to that as they.</q> But they say (saies he, and we say so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) <hi>We cannot confide in the Kings Oath.</hi> For my part (saies he) I think, <hi>that without repentance they will be damned,</hi> For saying so, (Yes, in the Court at Oxford, and in their mouthes, who damne
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159067:8"/> themselves every day] because they have so little <hi>charitie.</hi> Truly me thinks, this fellow has no charity at all, to judge them all damned persons, who cannot confide in the Kings Oath. I confesse we cannot do it, if we should die for it. We cannot, against so many Declarations from his hand, both in Ireland and England, &amp;c. True it is, some Declarations have been written touching his Majesties gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions that way, containing promises and vows too; But we must see him speak, that is, do what he speaks, not undo with his hand what he binds with his tongue. The <hi>Lord</hi> knows, we can appeal to Him, and clear our selves before His Majestie in point of charity towards our King; that we will not yeeld to the best in Oxford touching that matter. But charity is not blind; the Lord Christ will be tried by what he does; <hi>Go tell John what you have seen.</hi> If we see the hand (the practise the life) agreeable to the profession of the tongue, we have so much charity as to beleeve the man without an Oath: But if so be his hand be a contra-Remonstrance still to the profession of his mouth, then, though he promise and swear too, &amp; take the <hi>Sacrament</hi> upon it, if a Minister of Christ will give it, yet we have not so much charity as to beleeve him; and yet we have so much Faith as to beleeve our salvation not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, and the more firmly, the more plainly we see, <hi>That no trust is to be put in man:</hi> for we can cleave the faster to <hi>God,</hi> Who, we know, is faithfull; He hath promised and sworn too, and what He hath <hi>spoken with his mouth, He</hi> hath <hi>fulfilled with His hand</hi> a, which is foure times repeated to the praise of God himself, <hi>King</hi> of Kings, and <hi>Lord</hi> of Lords.<note place="margin">1 Kin 8. 2 Cron. 6. 1 Joh. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The man ceas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th not his Observation yet <hi>prating</hi> against his betters with <hi>malicious words,</hi> but as one beating the air, or contending with his shadow, like the fool in the Commody, he talks gracefully with himself, asketh himself questions, &amp; answers them as wisely, and wins all upon his Adversary, as the child does, that playes with himself. Truly I thought at first fight of his Observations, I could have blown them away with a breath, they were so light: But I see they have caused more paines, not for the gravity in them, for there is none at all, but for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Readers sake, that he may be fully sati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied touching them, and his <hi>Covenant</hi> that sacred Vow. I must therefore observe one thing more herein, before I passe from this his Observation, that he exceeds the child in folly, for he asketh himself one and the same question twise over, <hi>Wherefore took they up Armes?</hi> Then, after his manner, answers it with two Negatives, <hi>Nor for the establishing of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion, No.</hi> A little after, he asketh again the very same question: and answers with petty Ingeny, <hi>Marry that, I think, none but God knows, besides themselves, &amp;c.</hi> And yet the next line fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, he takes upon himself to judge, <hi>Wherefore they took up Armes;</hi> and to make the Reason clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to all the world (though yet he saies none but God knows it) by his Observations, which, how he hath done, let the Reader judge, by so much as he hath read already touching them: But since he is so wise (for I confesse it is a point of wisdom, and he hath shewed it in this, and in no one word else) to appeal to Gods knowledge in a case betwixt party and party, who vow and protest one and the same thing, <hi>To maintain the true Religion,</hi> and yet go away as crosse on to the other as heaven is to hell. Since, I say, both parties vow and protest here one and the same thing, to maintain this sacred thing, not to be once mentioned by faigned and polluted lips Since it is so, the Parliament appeals too, to God; <hi>God knows, Who in His good time will bring all to light;</hi> God knows, who knows the secrets of all hearts, and in His time will reveal them all. And in their appeal they say, God deal with them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the integritie of their hearts, and innocencie of their hands touching this matter. And now they know, that since there is an <hi>appeal</hi> to Him, the Judge of all the world, He will do right, for <hi>He is Judge himself;</hi> He will maintain His servants, and His Cause; When? Now He does it in all His peoples sight, though the Adversary will not see it; nor is there so full a manifestation of Gods righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement, for, and in behalf of His servants, and against His enemies as shall be, <hi>In Gods good time.</hi> When His Adversaries have filled-up their measures; when His friends are taken off from all their vain confidences; when all their strong-holds are down, their <hi>fenced</hi> Cities <hi>impoverished,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>thou trustedst</hi> a (Mark that). When will this be? It was answered before, but we must answer still,<note place="margin">Jer. 5.17.</note>
                  <hi>In Gods good time.</hi> Not ours; our time is now, Gods time, <hi>not yet:</hi> I do not intend these words to the ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of a fool. What will you say, if <hi>Bristow</hi> be taken first, and so an in-let open to all the <hi>Beasts</hi> of <hi>prey</hi> out of Ireland? Nay, what will you say if London be <hi>impoverished</hi> first. Then you will give-up the Cause as lost, and conclude the Parliament and their party were in the wrong all this while, and the Kings party in the right. God forbid, nay God forgive such a thought, that, because such a City is taken, and such servants of the Lord, are fallen in battell, therefore the Cause is fallen too; God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give such a thought; this fenced City, and that may be impoverished, because the inhabitants <hi>trusted in them:</hi> This and this servant of the Lord may fall in this warre, for the same reason, and so hath the best servant that ever God had in the world: But to conclude hence, that the cause is fallen, there we are too <hi>hast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> for the Cause is <hi>holy, just</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> will come-in for the defence of it, and the maintain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of it in His own time. When is that? Because thou wilt have an Answer to this; thou shalt have it, I will point thee to the time directly, when Gods manner is to come in to His ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159067:9"/> contending for his Cause: But looke to thy duty now, and prepare thy selfe for that time. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member still, I do not speake this in the eares of a foole, though I am content it be carried to <hi>Oxford.</hi> Do not content thy s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe with a little <hi>hope,</hi> a little <hi>patience;</hi> Say still, <hi>Lord increase my Faith,</hi> for it will be a rare thing then; he that thinkes now he stands, may fall then, for want of all the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, specially for want of <hi>Faith,</hi> (that Mother grace) to beleeve, that God will appeare in the <hi>Mount,</hi> at <hi>the Sea,</hi> even at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> When his Adversaries expectation is at the highest, and his People at the lowest: I have answered, <hi>Then is Gods Time.</hi> Reader, my heart is towards thee, and I would shrift thine heart and mine owne at this point. Have wee not need of Patience, <hi>All Patience?</hi> of Faith, all Faith? Gods time (usually that has been his manner) to awaken as a Mighty Man, when he is awakened by Prayer; and that is never commonly, till his servants are in a <hi>Perishing condition,</hi> (then it is <hi>Powred</hi> forth) when the floods of great waters are come-up to the neck; when the Ship of the Church,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.24.</note> is covered with waves (covered, marke that) till the waves are so proud, God <hi>seems</hi> to sleepe, to awaken his People, but then up he ariseth, for his Disciples are in a perishing condition, sinking downe to the place of Dragons. Then they Pray, <hi>(Save us Lord,)</hi> and give <hi>God no rest;</hi> then He comes-in and saves them, when all helpe from the creature is gon forth, at the <hi>fourth watch.</hi> He suffers his People to be tossed to and fro;<note place="margin">Mat. 14.15</note> The proud waters to beat-in upon them, all night long, then he comes-in and rebukes those Proud waters, and there is a calme. Reader, what ever <hi>Rushing</hi> thou hearest now,<note place="margin">Isa. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 13. Revel. 11.18. Revel. 11.16, 17.</note> like the noyse, or rushing of <hi>Mighty Waters,</hi> (for the Nations are angry) yet be not dismayed, but rather encouraged: It must be so, the Ship of the Church must be tossed. But the Prouder the waters, and the higher they rose, the nearer the Arke was to Heaven: and so it will be now. <hi>The Nations are angry,</hi> But the Lord Christ hath <hi>taken to Himselfe Power,</hi> and <hi>raigneth,</hi> therefore. doe not give-up the Cause for lost, (for it is against the Law of Heaven) till the <hi>fourth Watch</hi> be come and passed. What then? Then thou wilt never give over the Cause as l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st; for He will heare the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the destitute:</hi> In the time of extremitie, at the <hi>fourth Watch,</hi> He that came will come, for then his People see, <hi>Vaine is the helpe af man;</hi> and then they pray, <hi>Lord save us.</hi> I must prevent a mistake here, and then I have don with the <hi>Appeale,</hi> and <hi>set time</hi> of Deliverance, our <hi>Gods owne Time.</hi> Wee must not thinke, that <hi>God</hi> heares not the Prayers of his servants, but that Prayer onely, which they powre forth when they are in extremitie, sinking down into great waters, <hi>Lord save us, wee perish;</hi> wee must not thinke so, that God gives a returne to this Prayer onely, and hath given no Answer to all the rest. If there be such a mis-conceipt, the understanding must be unfolded, for it causeth a great mistake, and it is very dis-heartening Wee must know, there is a treasure of Prayers in heaven, for the Church on Earth, and not one of those are <hi>in vaine;</hi> God answers Prayers every day, wee see a returne of them every houre. I speake what the sober Reader knows perhaps better then my selfe; That the Church never saw such a returne of Prayers, since shee c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or from <hi>Babylon,</hi> then shee sees at this day. God forbid, that wee should thinke, God he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res not Prayers, and gives no Answer to them, because this Citie is taken, another is begirt round, and a third is in danger. Put downe these conclusions, and conclude thy soule under them.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 12.7. Dan. 11.34.</note>1. <hi>God</hi> may deliver <hi>the dearely beloved of his soule into the Enemies hands,</hi> not to dest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oy them, (for <hi>God</hi> is good to <hi>Israel</hi> still) but to <hi>purge</hi> and <hi>whiten them;</hi> for which end he useth the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Nobles of the world,</hi> as his <hi>Scullions</hi> to cleare-up and purge his vessels appointed unto honour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. (For I must huddle) we cannot judge of <hi>love</hi> or <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tred</hi> by outward administration of things; That which is,<note place="margin">Eccl 9.1. Mat 3.18.</note> before a man does not distinguish betwixt him <hi>that sweareth,</hi> and <hi>him that feareth an Oath:</hi> stay till <hi>God makes up his Jewells,</hi> then you <hi>shall discerne betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xt the righteous and the wicked.</hi> Now <hi>Israel</hi> are in straits, the Sea before them, but yee may be sure, these are Gods <hi>Israel.</hi> The right hand of the Adversary is lifted-up now, they are very prosperous; you are assured they are as the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> the Atheists, and Papists of the world, the chiefe Lords there. <hi>Israel</hi> now, as in old time, is marching towards a Promised Land, the Sea is before, the mountaines on each side, a proud Adversary behinde them, pressing on to hinder their passage. Will you thinke now, that the Adversary are the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of God, and <hi>Israel</hi> hated? No; It is cleane contrary, as you heard before. The Sea opens now, the waters cleave in sunder, to give <hi>Israel</hi> passage: the Adversary thinkes they open for him, that he may <hi>pursue, over-take, divide the spoyle.</hi> Thinkes he so? are those his proud thoughts? Then is his hope at the height, and rage too; Now <hi>stand still</hi> to behold the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alvation of God,</hi> for now is the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> (the fourth watch,) now <hi>God</hi> is <hi>looking-out upon the Host of his Enemies;</hi> and He will make them <hi>as still as a stone.</hi> The hopes of the Adversary must rise high, as their rage does, even to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: And his people must be laid low, they must be in a perishing condition, that <hi>God</hi> may be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their Salvation; For <hi>He will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide upon the Heavens for their help, and in his excellency on the skie.</hi> God will be glorious in their Deliverance; But</p>
               <p n="3">3. In his owne time, the <hi>fulnes of Time:</hi> As a stubborne <hi>Israelite</hi> once, (who counted <hi>Reforming</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:159067:9"/> a <hi>Killing;</hi> So may <hi>Israel</hi> now, put back Deliverance with their owne hands. His <hi>Moseses,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 2.14</note> the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full servants of the <hi>Lord,</hi> may have but a sight onely of that good Land, whereto God is bringing his People, and that is a great favour too. But our <hi>little ones,</hi> (of whom wee are so carefull, shall see yet more glorious things) for they have not been like their Fathers, unfaithfull in the Covenant: And if we can beleeve, we may see them too.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Can you conclude, this is the darkest time, with the Church; not <hi>the day,</hi> but the <hi>darkest night</hi> of <hi>Jacobs troubles:</hi> I beleeve you cannot conclude so, but if you can, then conclude, the morning is neare.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Lastly, for I will breake off, conclude thy soule under this truth, That, though <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>istow</hi> be taken, and <hi>London</hi> may be impoverished; Nay, though the Parliament should desert the Cause also, yet the <hi>Cause</hi> shall not miscarry; yet it shall be carried on, for the <hi>seed of Iacob</hi> have sought <hi>God</hi> in this thing; And they never <hi>sought God in vaine. Daniel</hi> heard terrible things, touching the troubles of the Church, and of her Adversaries prevailing against her;<note place="margin">Dan. 8.27.</note> and it afflicted <hi>Daniel</hi> very much (as it should do us) <hi>for he fainted, and was sicke certaine dayes:</hi> So deeply he was afflicted. And all these dayes, his Prayers were heard, yes every Prayer he had put-up before and after: <hi>For from the first day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 10.12.</note>
                  <hi>that thou didst set th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne heart to understand, and to chasten thy selfe before thy God, thy words were heard.</hi> So, Prayers put-up, ten, twenty, thirty, fourty yeares agoe, and so downward, were heard, and wee have seene their returne in all the Peoples sight: But yet the great returne will be, when God heares the Prayer of the <hi>Destitute:</hi> The prayer of His people sinking; when his People are in extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie; when they know not <hi>what to doe,</hi> when helpe, when refuge faileth: Such a time will be, and then <hi>God will appeare in his Glory;</hi> Then His people shall see, All his attributes displayed before their Eyes; His power, goodnes, mercy, &amp;c. And they shall say, Deliverance could not have come sooner, and have come so well: He stayed till the fourth Watch, but then he came best of all, and most welcome. A Calme is never so comfortable, as when ushered in with a storme. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nke on this, I pray you; The humble will thinke upon it and rejoyce, the proud will scorne at it, though it be <hi>Higgaion Selah,</hi> A thing greatly to be meditated upon. <hi>Thou answeredst them, O Lord our God:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 9 16</note>
                  <hi>thou wast a God that forgavest them, though thou tookest vengeance of their inventions.</hi> And so much to our <hi>Appeale:</hi> wee are resolved also to remit all to <hi>Gods owne time,</hi> the best time, even <hi>the sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Time.</hi> We proceed to his third Observation: He observes,</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">3. That the Parliaments Vow and Covenant, to stick to one another, is not a Vow, a <hi>Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> rather: A thing never don in a lawfull Warre, but in Conspiracies and Confederacies, which notes their inward guilt, and who were their Teachers, even their brethren the <hi>Scotts.</hi>
                  </q> See how bold this <hi>Novice</hi> is, he will condemne them, whom the King and Kingdome have cleared I will let it passe, though I could shew him <hi>how he exalts folly.</hi> He makes a use of this very uselesse and witlesse (yet I will make it serve me anon) and so he hath don his Observation. Now I will tell what <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> observes upon it; <q rend="margDblQuotes">That, sayes he, which is accounted Treason and Rebellion here below, is accounted the best obedience in heaven: Those, whom men call Rebells and Traytors,<note place="margin">Quae hic sunt malis in Coelo v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cantur bona.</note> God calls his best Subjects: That, which man calls a Conspiracy. God calls by its owne name, a <hi>striving to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for God,</hi> and the faith of the Gospel, the Crowne, and glory of a Kingdome. That is the Observation. Now I will reade two <hi>Cases,</hi> and, to use the <hi>Observators</hi> words, I shall make onely this use, To desire every honest man, to consider, which Covenant is a <hi>Combination:</hi> which side ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the just warre, and have the clearest conscience, and with them to joyne himselfe:</q> Then he will not joyne himselfe with an Army of Papists, <hi>English</hi> Monsters, <hi>French, Ir sh,</hi> Beasts in the shape of men: he will not enter himselfe with these <hi>Fighters</hi> against God. But who shall judge the justice of this warre? Not the <hi>Lord Keeper,</hi> nor Judge <hi>Heath:</hi> no such corrupt Judges. He will be the Judge, who judgeth righteous Judgement. Who has <hi>smitten his hand at thy dishonest gaine, and at thy bloud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezek. 22.13.</note>
                  <hi>which hath been in the midst of thee</hi> He is Judge himselfe. Wee shall see plainly how he has resolved two Cases, both touching the Justice of a warre. Wee must all stand now to his Arbitration, and submit. The first Case.</p>
               <p>The children of <hi>Reuben, Gad,</hi> and <hi>Manasseth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iosh. 22.10.</note> are dismissed by <hi>Joshua</hi> to their Possessions beyond <hi>Iordan;</hi> Returning thither, they built an Altar, a <hi>great Altar to see to.</hi> The children of <hi>Israel</hi> (the other Tribes) heare of this, That their Brethren have built an <hi>Altar;</hi> There is a jealousie presently in all the other Tribes, that their Brethren have don against Gods command and rule of worship, and then they will undo themselves and all <hi>Israel.</hi> They have transgress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the Commandement already (thought <hi>Israel</hi>) there will be an Idolatrous worship anon, which <hi>Israel</hi> are resolved to prevent spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily; <hi>So the whole Congregation of the Children of Israel</hi> gathered themselves together at <hi>Sh loh</hi> to <hi>parlie</hi> first, then <hi>to goe up to warre against their Brethren.</hi> A suspicion, a jealousie onely, that they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159067:10"/> had don against the Commandement, and would provoke a <hi>jealous God,</hi> was warrant sufficient to goe up to <hi>warre against their Brethren,</hi> if they cannot give a full and faire account, like <hi>Israelites,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that matter, which they did. And it is very notable, even the matter and manner of their account; They doe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t stand-it out, contesting with their Brethren in a case so cleared from the Word; <q rend="margDblQuotes">May wee not set up an Altar, and serve <hi>God</hi> after our owne manner, but you must controule us, and make warre with us your Brethren? Wee can set up an Altar against the <hi>Command,</hi> and yet worship <hi>God</hi> according to his command. Why do our Brethren of <hi>Israel</hi> enquire what we doe beyond the River? What do's that concerne <hi>Iudah?</hi> We will do what we please, but what ever we do, though wee build an Altar, and resolve to worship before it, yet wee professe to maintaine the true Religion, according to Covenant, and to make that our <hi>first worke.</hi>
                  </q> Had there been such an answer returned, it is cleare from the Context, That all <hi>Israel had warred with their Brethren.</hi> But the <hi>softnes</hi> and <hi>clearenesse</hi> of their Answer, returned to the heads of the thousands of <hi>Israel,</hi> is very notable; <hi>The Lord God of gods,</hi> and so forth, indeed we should observe both the matter and forme of their words, how they cleare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and their <hi>Altar</hi> too; so as there is a cleare understanding on both sides, and no more to do. The reading of this is abundantly enough to cleare the Parliaments case, and to justifie the managing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, were it carried on with that height of zeale, and resolution, as <hi>Israels</hi> warre was, though but in designe and upon suspicion onely. Here are <hi>Altars</hi> built, here and there and every where, against the expresse word of <hi>God</hi> to the contrary: <hi>The Lord God of gods, The Lord God of gods,</hi> He knows, that his worship is prophaned hereby; their hearts grieved, who should not be grieved; Altars have been built,<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 22, 23</note> they are maintained to this day in <hi>Rebebellion and transgression against the Lord,</hi> to <hi>turne from following Him.</hi> And this abomination is don, and maintained by the Lords of the world, the heads of the Land, who do professe to maintaine the true Religion; when indeed, they do all they can to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it. In <hi>Joshuahs</hi> dayes, as good a <hi>Leader</hi> as ever was after him; A suspicion, and jealousie onely of transgressing at this high point, <hi>Gathered all Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ael together to warre aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nst their Brethren.</hi>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a rebellion now really and in truth maintained and inforced with the Engines of warre, and Instruments of death upon <hi>Israel,</hi> a free People, by the haters of God, and all good men, servants of a <hi>strange God,</hi> and <hi>strangers to the Common-wealth of Israel,</hi> engaged upon this designe, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suance of it to the utter destruction of all the true <hi>Israel</hi> of God, whether this may not engage all <hi>Israel</hi> now to warre as it did then, I leave in the midst betwixt <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Oxford;</hi> and if there be the same zeale in <hi>Israel</hi> now, as was in <hi>Israel</hi> once, I know how it will be.</q> But to cleare the Justice of the warre yet more,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>udg. 19.</note> I passe-on to the other Case. A Levite and his wife turned-in to lodge in <hi>Gibeah</hi> of <hi>Benjamin:</hi> They are entertained there, and as they were <hi>making their hearts merry,</hi> certaine <hi>sonnes of Belial</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>set <hi>the old mans house</hi> (where they were) <hi>round about,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 22.</note> resolved to have their will, and they had it, and did <hi>a vile thing,</hi> for they <hi>forced</hi> the Levites Concub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, so as next morning shee was <hi>found dead upon the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eshold</hi> The husband gives notice to th' other Tribes, what <hi>lewdnesse</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> was committed in <hi>Israel</hi> The Tribes hearing thereof call a <hi>Parliament,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 29.</note> are gathered together <hi>foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand:</hi> All these arose, <hi>knit themselves as one man,</hi> were resolved, after they had taken <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Counsell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 7, 8. Ver. 10.</note> saying, <hi>Wee will not any of us goe to his Tent, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther will wee any of us turne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his house, till we have don to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>beah of Benjamin, according to all their folly they have wrought in Israel.</hi> So they require th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Brother <hi>Benjamin</hi> to deliver-up those children of <hi>Belial,</hi> which are in <hi>G beah,</hi> that <hi>wee may put them to death</hi> (as wee have resolved in our Parliament) and <hi>put away evill from Israel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 13.</note>
                  <hi>Benjamin</hi> are stout, they will not hearken, they will maintaine the true Religion, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Covenant, that shall be th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir prime worke still. And they will maintaine those <hi>Children of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial</hi> too; All this will agree together (as Christ and <hi>Belial</hi>) so they are resolved. A marveilous thing, that <hi>Benjamin</hi> knowing <hi>the judgement of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v. 1.32.</note>
                  <hi>that they who commit such things are worthy of death,</hi> yet <hi>take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>asure in them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t do them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Tribes do not sit <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rlying</hi> on the matter, they have considered on it already, taken advice and spoken their minds; And now they addresse themselves to God, have their warrant from Him, and then they <hi>went out to B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ttell against B njamin.</hi> They f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, indeed, before their Adversaries once and againe, for they were not yet prepared for a victory; they had not yet purged themselves, who went forth to purge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Brethren; nor narrowly looked into the evill of their hearts, as they should doe, who professed to put away <hi>Evill from Israel,</hi> nor had they come-up so close to God, as they did do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their falls (of this anon.) The third time they are commanded to go-up against <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured the victory:<note place="margin">Ver. 43. Ver. 48.</note> Then <hi>Gibeah was smitten,</hi> and <hi>burnt with fire,</hi> the <hi>Benjamites</hi> were <hi>trod downe with ease, twenty and five thousand men: also they set on fire all the Cities that they came to.</hi> The Case now is Paral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l with that, and the Justice of the warre exceeds it: First, Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> rise-up then, beset a house <hi>round about,</hi> and <hi>heat at the dores.</hi> Here they have don so much and more, they have beset two Kingdoms, beaten downe the house of the Church and State <hi>to their Power.</hi> These
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159067:10"/> are demanded by the Parliament; <q rend="margDblQuotes">Deliver us the men the Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> that we may put them to death, and put away evill from <hi>Israel</hi> (It is high time, if it be not past)</q> There is no harkening to this voyce; But a rough hand is put forth against the Parliament, because of this demand; and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of those sons of Belial, King, Queen and Nobles put forth all their power, to destroy the House, and beat down two Kingdoms. No, I must say, if I will be so mad as others are, these put forth their strength for the defence of the House of Parliament, and for the building-up of two Kingdoms. The House of Parliament do pretend onely, their own private ends, but the King &amp; Queen with their loyall Subjects with them, intend really and indeed <hi>to maintain the true Protestant Religion,</hi> his <hi>Majesties just Power,</hi> and <hi>the just power and priviledges of Parliament;</hi> and their loyall subjects in Oxford can sweare the truth of all this; he that hath so little faith as to doubt thereof, shall be <hi>damned</hi> sure enough without Repentance, saies the open mouth from Oxford, put in Print by <hi>Leichfeild</hi> there. These men shall not have all the talk, I will put in a question here, which the Adversary shall resolve, but no sober man will beleeve him. The Queenes <hi>purchase</hi> beyond the Seas, her <hi>exchange</hi> there for Engines of warre and instruments of Death; what to do with these in England? A strange question: It is a damnable sin to make such a question. They answer, to defend the House of Parliament, and to build-up (not to beat down) as these Engines use to do, they have a contrary working in a Queenes hands to build-up) three Kingdomes: therefore the Queen exchanged the Jewels (the Kingdomes Jewels) made that purchase, to establish the Kingdom; therefore she appointed <hi>her loyall</hi> subjects to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set the House round,</hi> and beat at the doores in defence of the House and Houshold. That was the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and it is damnable to think otherwise. I will not speak a word here by way of Reply. We have seen the Paralel, how things do now relate to these children of Belial, besetting the House round, and beating at the doores, Now we must see what these <hi>children</hi> did in the streets, and how that relates to the present. what is done now.</p>
               <p>They <hi>forced a Concubine then,</hi> the Levites <hi>wife,</hi> as we read. But there is no such <hi>lewdnesse</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted now, no sure, it were damnable to think so. The King hath sworn, and he makes his loyall Subjects to swear so too, and to enter Covenant upon it, that, as power shall be given into their hands, they will so manage it, as their <hi>first endeavour</hi> shall be the defence of the <hi>Laws,</hi> just Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subject: very well; but then they must not force women nor maidens neither, for it is against the <hi>Rights</hi> and Liberties of the Subject. They do not, they have swo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, and have entred into Covenant, that they will do no wrong, but all the Right that can be. May we beleeve them? Yes, if you will beleeve what they say at Oxford, and sweare too, for it is all one with them. Reader, thou must not laugh here, unlesse thou canst laugh as <hi>God</hi> laughs, with an indignation and zeal against these <hi>children of Belial,</hi> who have forced wives and maids too; have wrought villanies, and lewdnesse in Israel, and defiled two Kingdoms with it, from corner to corner. The Observator hath concluded, <hi>That all the Kings Army are Papists.</hi> And shall we regard what Papists sweare and vow? They vow to do all the mischief they can; to commit villanie and lewdnesse in Israel <hi>to their power:</hi> and as they do. We have observed but little if we have not observed, what vows Papists make, and how they <hi>stand to them.</hi> And yet I am not assured by what the Observator saies, that all the Kings Army are Papists. I know who would be Angry, that such an <hi>Hellish Rout</hi> should be called by his name, <hi>Papa.</hi> Indeed it is an abuse, for there are many English monsters there fighting against their own countrey; and <hi>Irish</hi> Rogues and Traitors (as they call the Parliament) who have oft and oft washed their hands in the blood of Mothers and their Infants and boasted of it, and yet are very active at the Court, and very gracious there. They are there, whom the Scripture cals <hi>roaring Lyons</hi> and <hi>ravening Wolves.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zeph. 3.3.</note> There are some French too, we know them. The most of them are beasts in the shape of men. And the whole Kingdom is assured, that it is the most bloodie mischievous most accursed Army, that ever was upon the face of the earth. They have and they will, to their power destroy Religion, that which should be kept <hi>pure and undefiled,</hi> the Queen hath to her power, (and she hath al in her hands, but God hath put a hook in her Nose, and a bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le in her lips) she hath with her loyall Subjects, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hildren of Belial,</hi> she hath (I will speak it all in a word) she hath <hi>forced the Spouse of Christ,</hi> I say, <hi>forced her</hi> before their <hi>Lords face.</hi> I wil sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no more: But if so be the <hi>Lord</hi> of this Spouse, the <hi>Lord God</hi> of <hi>gods,</hi> the <hi>Lord God of gods</hi> does not require this at the King and Queens hands; If He does not <hi>force</hi> them, for <hi>forcing</hi> His Queen before His face, and their own consciences in the light; if the <hi>Lord God</hi> of gods does not <hi>force</hi> them (for the time and manner how, the Church remits unto their Lords hand:) But if he does not <hi>force</hi> them, then the <hi>Lord God</hi> of gods is not a true and faithfull God, keeping Promise and Covenant for ever, whereof His servants have not the least doubt; The <hi>Lord</hi> will <hi>force</hi> them, that have <hi>forced</hi> His Queen before His face. He will drive them, as the dust before the whirl-wind. The Church makes no doubt of that; sound Repentance, a <hi>sorrow after a godly sort,</hi> shall not be able to keep off a Temporall judgement. We have heard what this <hi>lewdnesse</hi> was, and what it is, and how far the <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llanies</hi> now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159067:11"/> those then▪ then the <hi>warre</hi> now will exceed too in the justice and equitie of it. I need not stand upon that, I will set down two Observations here, which shall answer these two, we received from Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, the first is, which answers his second.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">The Parliament have vowed never to lay down Armes so long as the Papists now in Arms against the Parliament (as they say) shall be kept from the Justice of it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Very wel, and they have an example for it, which exceeds The Parliament vow not to lay down Armes; Israel vowed not to go back to their tents (as sometimes the Scots did) before the Delinquents were delivered-up to Justice, and hanged-up by the necks. Why, but this excludes all hope of <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iud. 20.8.</note> Yes that it do's, wee should be sorry else. And yet the Devill is <hi>hammering</hi> at it againe, he would faine have us at peace with him, and with his sworn servants: And we have a pretty good mind to it at this time, though we have sworn, and sworn againe, That we will have no peace till his sworn servants all are <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut a sunder,</hi> and then we shall have a <hi>peace</hi> of Gods giving. Pray tell me, what <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation</hi> can be here? The house was <hi>beset round</hi> then, (two Kingdoms now) a Concubine, a Levites wife, a poore obscure woman (yet her Lord, and <hi>Gods</hi> Law, and all <hi>Israel</hi> take care of her, mark that) was <hi>forced</hi> then; In a word, The <hi>Spouse</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> is <hi>forced</hi> now, that glorious Woman, the dearly beloved of His soul, shee is <hi>forced</hi> before her <hi>Lords</hi> face; What accommodation? <hi>Israel</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not abate an <hi>ace,</hi> not with their Brother, they will be the stricter with him: Brother <hi>Benjamin</hi> give-up these <hi>Children of Belial</hi> to Justice, that we may <hi>put them to death,</hi> and <hi>put away evill from Israel;</hi> Tell me, and shew thy selfe a man, can there be a more reasonable demand? Can there be an <hi>ace</hi> aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here? Why then, no hope of accommodation. Yes, for these <hi>Children of Belial,</hi> intended the defence of the old mans house, and of the Levites Concubine, &amp;c Let who will answer, for I will not, when such Children are said to maintaine Lawes, and just Rights, who breake all Lawes, and do all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice that is conceivable.</p>
               <p>Why but <hi>Benjamin,</hi> that Tribe, might do and maintain Judgement and Justice, and yet maintain these <hi>Children of Belial,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>No, that was not possible; It more then seems that <hi>Benjamin</hi> tooke pleasure in them; and that he was <hi>as one of</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Obadiah.</note>
                  <hi>them. Benjamin</hi> cannot defend the Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> those that breake all yoakes, and have cast off all bands, and not be, in so doing, a <hi>Childe of Belial</hi> himselfe, a destroyer of himselfe and people. It is a cleared Case: I give now my second Observation, which answers his third; whch is <q rend="margDblQuotes">That wee, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> taking a vow to assist one another in pursuance of this warre [against those Children of <hi>Belial</hi>] do make a <hi>Combination</hi> or a <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> which was never don in a lawfull warre.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> Yes, It was, but no Conspiracy, no Combination; for thus it was; <hi>Foure hundred thousand Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> assemble themselves, for Consultation first, then they are resolved to <hi>stick close together,</hi> not to part so far, <hi>as any of them to goe to his Tent:</hi> The people <hi>arose,</hi> sayes the Text, were gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>knit together as one man.</hi> Foure hundred thousand as one man, acted by one soul, all of <hi>one minde,</hi> and <hi>of the same judgement.</hi> What was that? <q rend="margDblQuotes">That these wicked, <hi>Children of Belial,</hi> must be put away, else evill cannot be put away;</q> What a sweet agreement was here? Yes, and this they call at <hi>Oxford</hi> a <hi>Combination;</hi> The Children of <hi>Benjamin</hi> are knit together all as one man, with the Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> to defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d them from the justice of the Law, yet this is no <hi>Combination.</hi> Well, let them say what they will, wee must say as the truth is, and so wee must practise; Wee must all arise <hi>as one man;</hi> we must be <hi>kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> together for this thing, The <hi>putting away these Children of Belial,</hi> and <hi>evill from Israel.</hi> That it hath not been don sooner, hath caused all this mischiefe. Wee must be knit together <hi>as one man,</hi> in a sweet concord and agreement touching this matter, as acted by one soule, of <hi>one mind, and the same judgement.</hi> Why, but though the <hi>house</hi> of the Church is <hi>beset round</hi> by these Children of <hi>Belial,</hi> and they have <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ced</hi> the <hi>Spouse of Christ</hi> before their <hi>Lords face,</hi> yet may there not be some way taken for an Accommodation? Yes that it may very well; It is not too late, yet after our <hi>Vow</hi> and <hi>Protestation:</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f wee will beleeve <hi>hearsay,</hi> the greatest lyar in the world; The <hi>Nobles</hi> are upon it at this v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry houre, <hi>how to A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>commodate a Peace.</hi> I will never beleeve it, that the <hi>Nobles,</hi> who, as their manner is, sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd themselves for Christ, lay-out themselves for His Glory; minde his House, so as they forget their owne, That these can thinke of an <hi>Accommodation</hi> now: and yet I say it is reported, they have drawn up <hi>Propositions,</hi> tending that way, and even concluded: In short, these: <q rend="margDblQuotes">Let the King have his desire compleated, touching his <hi>strong-holds</hi> upon the Land &amp; Sea, &amp;c. What he will desire also touching the <hi>Assembly</hi> of <hi>Min sters</hi> now, &amp;c. And the Kings good people shall have their desire compleated too; All the <hi>horrid Rebells</hi> and Traytors shall be delivered up into their hands (this will content his people, for then his Majestie makes good all he hath vowed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised.) And his good People sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll do with these <hi>horrid</hi> Rebels as pleaseth them, put them to what death they please (except one) cut them assunder with the sword, hang them, sow them in a bag and downe them, or starve them to death, which pleaseth best: what other death they can invent, except
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159067:11"/> the plague of Pestilence, for that is as the Kings warre now, <hi>Immediately from his Warrant:</hi> So that stroake, <hi>Immediately</hi> from <hi>Gods hand.</hi>
                  </q> You now have the summe, and Result of the <hi>Consultation,</hi> as People foolishly report in the Citie, but no sober man can beleeve it, That the Nobles, who have knowledge, and a zeale according to their knowledge, will goe about such a worke so impossible; To Accommodate a Peace for Christ, whose House is beset round now, and His Spouse forced before His face, and his Servants all have vowed, That they will not lay downe Armes till these <hi>horrid</hi> Rebells be given up to the Justice of the Court. Justice of the Court! That is mainly intended, and that is the report too, and the Kings Promise and vow also; "So soone as he has his demands, his loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects shall have their demands, all the <hi>horrid</hi> Rebels given up into their hands, as aforesaid. Look you with all your eyes, what a mistake here is, I will not call it by any other name, a mistake: His Majesty will be pleased, that all the <hi>horrid</hi> Rebells shall be given-up to be cut in sunder, hanged, drowned, starved. But who are these <hi>horrid</hi> Rebells? Reade the Kings <hi>Proclamation touching his good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards London.</hi> There you shall reade of an <hi>horrid Rebellion,</hi> charged upon that Citie, most eminently knowne above all the Cities in the world (Blessed be God) at this day, standing for God, and His Christ. This is the <hi>horrid</hi> and rebellious Citie; These are the horrid Rebells and Traytors there; who? All the faithfull in the Parliament, in the Citie, All that have entertained the <hi>destitute,</hi> the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therless,</hi> the <hi>Cast-out;</hi> All the godly Ministers, and godly People (none else are destitute or cast-out now) whom the King by the hand of his murtherers, hath robbed and pillaged, for, if he hath not commanded it, he hath suffered it to be don. And these <hi>Faithfull</hi> in the Parliament, in the Citie, these shall be delivered-up to the sword, for these are his <hi>horrid Rebells,</hi> he means no other; It were a vaine conceipt to thinke, that the King will put away his Queen, [as you know who <hi>put away their wives</hi> being Daughters of a strange god: and may they dwell together, and the Blessing of God upon them, which will be, when they <hi>turne from Idols</hi> to <hi>serve the living God</hi>] you do not thinke the King will give-up to Justice, the <hi>horrid Rebells</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or in <hi>England;</hi> for these are his <hi>Right</hi>-men and best Subjects now in whom he confides, and his soule delighteth. Reader, thou do'st not thinke he means these, when he tells his Parliament, <hi>The Delinquents shall be given-up to Iustice.</hi> The King means as aforesaid, those that will not vow obedience to his <hi>will,</hi> not <hi>Aray</hi> themselves to warre by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie from his <hi>Immediate</hi> Warrant. Beleeve then, that it is as impossible to accommodate a Peace here, as it is to accord most contrary things, which stand in an eternall opposition, as the two Poles, or <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Belial.</hi> It is as possible to set those starres <hi>South</hi> and <hi>North</hi> together one by the other, to bring-up Hell to Heaven, as to bring this businesse to a faire Accommodation. Therefore wee will not beleeve <hi>hearesay;</hi> These men, (they are but men, and they know it, I purposely forbeare titles now of <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Worthies,</hi> now that the honour and glory of Christ is so trampled upon in the world) these men are better imployed now, in making their Peace with God, in thinking on away, that will make themselves <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>honorable indeed:</hi> Whereas, to consult about a way to Accommodate the cause and quarrell of Christ, and not in his own way, is to consult shame to their own house, and rebuke to the Church of Christ Wee are where wee were, like a Ship in a tempest, tossed much, but has made no way. The Law must be satisfied, give her-up these Rebells and Traytors <hi>indeed</hi> to the justice of it, all the reason in the world it should be so; Petty theeves, who steale for their belly, are led to the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes by great theeves, sayes one, and the matter is dispatched quickly: Give us-up these great <hi>theeves,</hi> mighty <hi>hunters, horrid Rebells,</hi> who spoyle and destroy Kingdomes; give them up, it must be don; It is the demand of the <hi>Lord Christ,</hi> and of his People in Covenant with him for this thing; The Lord Christ His House is beset round with <hi>Children of Belial;</hi> they have to their power beat downe the house, forced his Spouse before his face. Now He that set his <hi>Right-foot</hi> upon the Sea, and his <hi>left</hi> on the Earth, hath sworn that He will be avenged of these <hi>Sonnes,</hi> He will ease himselfe of these Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries: His faithfull servants have committed themselves and this Cause into his hands, and thither they looke, and laugh at all other wayes of Accommodation.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">But if there be not a Peace, the <hi>House</hi> will be beat downe, and quite destroyed, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> therefore give us Peace, say wee, upon any termes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Then take it and perish with it; but we speake like our selves, Men of small understanding; <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes"> let us do our duty, make good our Vow, <hi>Not to lay downe Armes, till the wicked be destroyed, and evill put away: Leave God to his worke,</hi> and <hi>rest assured in this, He will looke to his House and Houshold;</hi> He will be <hi>good</hi> to them, how ever they fare in the world; <hi>good</hi> to them in all Conditions, in all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations, in all Dispensations of mercies, and distributions of sorrowes, still, still <hi>good</hi> to <hi>Israel,</hi> the pure in heart, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </q> It is not possible to say any thing against the lawfulnesse of this warre: But this may be said to discourage the undertaking of the like againe: <hi>Israel</hi> falls before <hi>Benjamin,</hi> heapes upon heapes, once and againe. At the first on-set <hi>twenty and two thousand men were destroyed downe to the ground.</hi> The second time, 18000. <hi>men that drew the Sword.</hi> What then? Yet <hi>Israel</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:159067:12"/> must judge themselves as they did, not judge the lawfulnesse of the warre. They question how they managed the warre, and what Conquest they had made over themselves; They did not question this, whether the Children of <hi>Belial</hi> ought to <hi>be put to death, that evill may be put away from Israel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Case is ours. Gods <hi>Israel</hi> fall here and there. What then? Therefore the warre is not lawfull. God himselfe denies this, the contrary is upon everlasting Record: The warre is lawfull, if you use it lawfully; the warre is good, but it is ill managed; There <hi>Israel</hi> layes all the blame, as they ought to do, and they gaine exceedingly every day by their losses, setting their faces more <hi>stedfastly</hi> to God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have turned their backes upon their Adversaries; rising higher in their Faith, the lower they fell. If <hi>Israel</hi> are lying upon their faces in deep humiliation, and, according to their Charge, are resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to search their tents, and their hearts, and to Cast-out the <hi>accursed thing</hi> (which makes <hi>Israel</hi> turne their backs) if <hi>Israel</hi> do now, as then, rise-up after their <hi>fall,</hi> still to come-up closer to their God;<note place="margin">Num. 23.24.</note> if so, they shall, rise-up as a <hi>great Lyon, and not lie downe till he eate of the prey, and drinke of the bloud of the slaine.</hi> Then wee shall chase our Adversaries, and as <hi>Israel</hi> did, <hi>tread them downe with ease.</hi> In the meane time, the Adversary must be lifted up with successe, that he may fall the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er anon, and with more amazement. But whether wee stand, or fall, yet this is a cleared Case, <hi>Israel</hi> have a just warrant to warre with those, who resist and will not <hi>give-up Delinquents to the Justice of the Law;</hi> And if the successe be not answerable to expectation, wee must judge our selves, and the manner of managing the warre; Whether wee have come up to God touching that matter; whether the <hi>accursed thing</hi> be removed from out of the <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>tent;</hi> Whether, when the <hi>Children of Belial</hi> have been in our hands, wee have put them to death. Certainly, that is the duty which God requires at those hands, whereinto he has put the <hi>Sword.</hi> If there be an Arch-Traytor in the Kingdome, as sure enough there is, who has dealt corruptly in the Covenant, and falsified the great trust of the <hi>Lord</hi> the <hi>Charge of Soules,</hi> sitting at the sterne of the Church, in the highest place there; this man must be put to death, else he will, as he has don, cause <hi>Israel</hi> to fall before their Adversaries. And so of others, who have been chiefe in transgression, and carrying-on that Designe, and the warre against Citie and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom also. But for those, who were drawne-in, and betrayed, as it were, to betray others, mercy may be showne, for it lessens the Case. I know my place, and my station. But this is an eternall truth, <hi>Ch ldren of Belial must be delivered-up, not to be put in prison, but to be put to death.</hi> What then? <hi>And put away evill from Israel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was necessary to touch upon Israels fals here in his lawfull warre; Because, it is said ordinarily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any disaster, or fall in battell; <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                     <hi>Do not ye see how God fights against you?</hi> that He is an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to you; and would tell you plainly, if you would hear, <hi>that your Cause is naught?</hi> And see you not what successe the other party hath?</q>
               </p>
               <p>No indeed, we do not see th'one or the other. And yet, we thank God, our eye sight is cleared tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this matter. We do see, that these and these on the Churches side are fallen; this City and that taken. We see all this, that <hi>the Sword devoureth one as well as another:</hi> And it displeaseth us not, for it is the <hi>Lords</hi> Sword, it pleaseth us, that He doth what pleaseth Him: His servants do professe hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, they know <hi>love</hi> rather then <hi>hatred, by all that is before them:</hi> their God will do them good by all. Blessed be God, the wise God, He will suffer His people to fall before the Adversary, that they may <hi>fall upon their face,</hi> deep in humiliation, and enquire into the Cause; why it is so, <hi>that Israel turn their backs?</hi> And then they are put to make enquirie into their <hi>hearts,</hi> and <hi>teats,</hi> there to find out <hi>the accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thing.</hi> The onely wise God indeed! He will not give-up this Army of Papists into His peoples hands, till they have done their <hi>Lords</hi> pleasure, served Him as <hi>scullions</hi> to <hi>purge</hi> and to <hi>whiten</hi> His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as was said. Gods people shall not be <hi>masters</hi> of the <hi>Feild,</hi> till they be <hi>masters</hi> of <hi>themselves.</hi> They shall not be <hi>Conquerours</hi> over their Enemies, these shall not be <hi>subdued</hi> under them, till His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple shall set their faces <hi>stedfastly</hi> to God, to <hi>subdue in them all iniquitie.</hi> He will not have His people <hi>Lords</hi> over others, and servants to their own lusts God forbid. And while this great victory is gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over themselves, I meane, while <hi>God</hi> is making His people more then Conquerours, He helps His people with a <hi>little help,</hi> so much as shall keep His people in heart, and keep-up His cause in all the peoples sight. And when they are at a losse, as now they are, it is to make them gainers: And when they fall, as now they do, it is to make them stand the more firmly in the strength of God, and power of His might. And this is a great matter which the Adversary mistakes, while he thinks, <hi>God is against His people.</hi> No: He is against His Adversaries. What He seems to be towards His people, is to make His people set their faces the more earnestly to heaven. The Adversary thinks God will <hi>undo</hi> His people. No, God never said so; But He hath said, <hi>I will undo all that afflict thee</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph. 3.19.</note>: and so He will. And now He is doing of it, even now when He gives the Adversary successe; lets him prosper in an evill way; when <hi>God</hi> (after the Adversary hath shut our light) shuts the eye, and heardens the heart, and suffers him to blunder-on against a drawn sword; when he sees a way opened for Israels passage, and he thinks
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159067:12"/> the way is opened for him, to pursue Israel; these be sad strokes, this is to be <hi>against a man,</hi> or a people, or an Army. To <hi>fall</hi> before an Enemy may be a mercy: but for an Adversary to stand out stoutly against God and His people is a sore judgement, and a fore-runner of a fall, which shall ruine the Adversarie <hi>utterly,</hi> for ever and ever, Amen.</p>
               <p>Reader, if thou art come so farre, thou hast heard the <hi>Observator</hi> and me both; I will not be foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confident now, that this which I have done will make some <hi>Proselytes,</hi> (I will use the Observators words, though improper) some <hi>Proselytes</hi> I say, and thy self one amongst the rest. I will not declare my hope that way, though it hath a better bottom then the Observators <hi>hope</hi> hath. This I would command of thee: consider the <hi>Covenants</hi> well, for as the <hi>Observator</hi> saith well, <hi>It is a fearfull thing to mock God solemnly.</hi> Consider with all thy heart what is observed by us both, what hath a clear agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the Rule of Heaven, the Laws of men, and practise of all Gods people in all ages. And what is contrary to all this, reject it. Then consider what is said with the mouth, and then see what is done with the hand: While thou art considering all this (now is a considering time) I would give thee sound counsell. Go crosse to all the Observator hath said, for he hath gone crosse to a common light; but specially refuse his counsell, which is this in his 4. page: <hi>Let a man alwayes have recourse to his own breast, and aske counsell there.</hi> No but do not: I will not forbear him; he is a <hi>fool,</hi> and would make thee a <hi>fool</hi> too: if thou wilt ask counsell of thy self, be <hi>thy own Teacher,</hi> thou hast a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>fool</hi> to thy Master, who, as the times are, will make thee a <hi>fool</hi> and mad both. Hearken to what I shall say; Have recourse to <hi>God,</hi> ask counsell at His mouth: do it <hi>alwayes,</hi> and do it heartily: then, though many Nobles perish with their Honors, many wise men perish with their wisdom, many learned men perish with their learning, yet thou shalt understand the way and fear of the <hi>Lord. His secrets are with them that fear Him.</hi> He <hi>will beautifie the meek with salvation.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 35.8.</note> The humble shall understand their way, the <hi>way-faring men though fools, shall not erre therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now that I have cleared the <hi>warre,</hi> the lawfulnesse of it, by the most cleared example; and our <hi>way</hi> in managing of it: I had done now, but that I must say something to my poore Countrey-men, who have something to say against taking <hi>Covenant,</hi> which is this. First:</p>
               <p>We need not be commanded to vow, we can vow and sweare too, and forswear also, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> it is our practise every day.</p>
               <p>See! poore souls! they glory in their shame, and make boast of their wickednesse; it is their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and folly too: I will strike at the <hi>root</hi> anon. In the meane time they must speak like men, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> if they look to be answered. They say, or it is said for them.</p>
               <p>If you enjoyn this vow upon the poore people, they will forswear themselves. It is required, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> they should be <hi>humble,</hi> and they cannot be <hi>humble.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You should say they <hi>will</hi> not. You fault the <hi>power,</hi> when the <hi>will</hi> is too blame. Again, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> this Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is false, they are not commanded, by man, to be humble, as good command an old Oake to fall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us; the Oake cannot be commanded, but they are intreated to think seriously of that, which, well pondered on, may make them humble. Again, so I huddle-up great matters, there is no more required of them, but what is in their power to do, and compasse of their vocation. Onely note this, a <hi>Pearle</hi> is a pearle a precious and excellent thing, though a swine be a swine still, and will do like a swine; you know what.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> But we cannot think it a lawfull Vow, for we vow to fight against our lawfull Prince.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> It is not <hi>against</hi> him, but <hi>for</hi> him, to deliver his sacred Person from out of the hands of murtherers; our <hi>Land</hi> from out of the hand of spoilers; our <hi>Parliament</hi> (who stand-up for us, and our just rights) from the hands of oppressors, and sorest <hi>task masters;</hi> the laws of God and man from <hi>sons</hi> of <hi>Belial,</hi> who would make all void, null, and of none effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> We have taken the Oath of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Allegeance</hi> both.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> It is well you have: I pray you enquire now into both; you have vowed to stand-up against forraign power. Your vows are upon you, do thereafter; stand up now, for now a forraigne power is pressing in upon you with all its might Ask at the Tower, heare and see what instruments were prepared to bring in a <hi>strange god,</hi> and a power <hi>strange</hi> to England. You have vowed Allegeance to the King, to obey him, <hi>ruling by Law,</hi> according to the law of Heaven: you have not vowed to obey his <hi>private will,</hi> for that is to obey the <hi>lusts of men,</hi> breaking and making void the laws of <hi>God,</hi> the Rights and Priviledges of a free people.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> But the King will maintain all these, the <hi>true Religion,</hi> also (which is the main) we will and must beleeve him, for he hath protested it, taking the <hi>Sacrament</hi> upon it from the hand of an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> Good people, be not deceived, many things are <hi>battled</hi> upon the Kings name (as we sometimes
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159067:13"/> said in Oxford <hi>(i. e.)</hi> charged upon him, which never came into his thoughts; that sacramentall vow, we read of, might be Printed in London, for the Divell is abroad now, and all his Instruments are very active there; A great d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al of forgery, false dealing, there is, whereby to deceive the very <hi>Elect</hi> if it could be. There is a notable invention too concerning the most famous Scholar, for piety and learning both that is in the world And yet I do not know, what he may do, and what he may suffer to be done,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.3</note> who will take to himself that <hi>name, Arch-Bishop, Great-Bishop,</hi> proper and peculiar onely to <hi>Christ</hi> our <hi>Lord.</hi> If a man assumes that name, it is a <hi>name of Blasphemies.</hi> So let it passe.</p>
               <p>But suppose, the King did vow after such a manner, as we read, truly it is a thing much to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his pernicious Councell hath drawn him very farre; his foot is entred deep into blood, and then we know, what men have said, and what they have done, and thought themselves in the right way, and that in all they have said or done, they have done God <hi>good service;</hi> So blinded their eyes may be, and so brawned their hearts. It was <hi>Sauls</hi> case, before he was <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Luthers</hi> too. But this was their plea, <hi>they did it out of ignorance:</hi> And that makes men very conceited of what they say, and do, very proud and st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffe, resolved in their way. Let us call to mind here, that the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> Daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, vowed as much as this to the men of Suffolke, to engage their help to make her Queene. When she had her desire, it is very legible that she did most contrary to her Protestation, nay she trampled upon their heads, who gave forth their hands to raise her to the Throne. The story is long but very notable, I have done with it. Onely this, the heart is an <hi>Abysse,</hi> a deep, which the wisest man (a man and no more) that ever was upon earth, could never bottom. But truly, I am halfe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded the King may vow and protest all this, and go according to his Principles. For what hath he protested?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That he intends the establishment of the true Protestant Religion.</hi> It may well be so: and that the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> protested as much once; so will the <hi>Queene</hi> now, and the most notorious Rebels and most known Papists. Why? Can we imagine, that the Queene hath taken all this pains, been at all this cost, parted with the <hi>Jewels</hi> of a Kingdom, prepared such instruments of death, to bring-in and <hi>force</hi> upon us a <hi>false Religion,</hi> under that notion, in her conceit? Do we think the Pope a fool, all his Cardinals mad, and their Jesuites b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utish; that they have contested so many hundred yeers with <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> and <hi>sword,</hi> (and will contest till they be sent to their own place) to maintain a Religion neither <hi>Protestant</hi> nor <hi>true?</hi> No, no: I tell you truly, the <hi>light</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> which is in a man, and he cannot put it out, hates <hi>falshood</hi> under that notion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but his Majestie saies more; his eye is upon an excellent pattern, whereto he will <hi>form</hi> himself, and his Religion <hi>as in the happy dayes of Queene Elizabeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> His Bishops abuse him fearfully. They <hi>perswade</hi> his Majestie to force in their Power again, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction; to set them-up again. What then? let the Bishops alone with the rest, then they will do as they have done, establish the true Protestant Religion, after a form and patterne, <hi>as it was in Queene Maries dayes;</hi> Just so, after that pattern, witnesse all their words, votes, actions and contrivances ever since those dayes upward to the 29. of December, 1641. unto this very day. And this is enough for that: onely Reader know this for thy good, that we must not look back to those who were in the dark to us, yet saw very much, newly peeping out of the mist; nor to those times, dark times in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ours, and the <hi>lights</hi> set up amongst us now at this day; we must not look <hi>back</hi> to what this <hi>Queene</hi> did, or what that King; no, we must look <hi>forward</hi> to our pattern, as we have our <hi>Lord Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ist</hi> our <hi>Leader</hi> and <hi>Commander<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> as we have Him for our patterne, His Word for our rule, so the Assembly guide their Counsels, not by what other Churches do: but by <hi>what is wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tten,</hi> so they must do. I would not be mistaken here, I do not diminish one myte from the excellent worth of that <hi>glorious</hi> Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; many Daughters did worthily, but she exceeded th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m all, and her name is as a <hi>precious Ointment powred forth.</hi> Reformation then was carried-on very farre and hopefully, considering the time, and the opposition of the Bishops. But the <hi>Lord</hi> knows it were a great dishonour to his Majesty to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thereafter, now in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se dayes. He hath vouchsafed more <hi>light,</hi> and therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e we must conforme thereafter; If the Bishops (for their hand is here) will look back, they must look back as farre as the Apostles dayes. But if they will look back to Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes (though a glorious Princes) we know their mind very well, and what is their end, they will quickly turn all back, so as it shall be as it <hi>was in Queen Maries dayes:</hi> that is cert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in It follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Without any connivance at Popery.</hi> Connivance, what is that? halfe Latine and more; in plaine English it is <hi>winking.</hi> His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stie ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> take the Sacrament upon it, that he doth not <hi>winke</hi> at Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Poper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> stareth him in the face, He looks Popery in the face, he looks upon it with open face, and he sets his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e upon the maintainers of it, for good, how bloodie soev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r these are; And shews unto these such f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vour, as he sheweth to those he delighteth in: Well, but what ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r is <hi>spoken,</hi> his good people will look what is <hi>done:</hi> and discern very well, what way the heart is carried, by that <hi>delight</hi> the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:159067:13"/> heart taketh: if in those, who are the <hi>excellent</hi> of <hi>the earth,</hi> then so; If in those, who are <hi>haters</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and goodnesse, then so; which if there were no more, yet is this very sufficient to give satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on touching this matter.</p>
               <p>But we poore people are in this (onely) like our sheep, which will follow as they see others go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, so can we: And a miserable case it is; We know not in the world what way to take, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                  </label> nor to which side to joyne in this <hi>warre.</hi> One party vows, so doth the other, that they are in the Right: so say the other; and both enter into Covenant touching this matter. Alas, what shall we poore simple ones do! we would fain fit still and be of neither side, that pleaseth best; but the destruction comes home to our gates.</p>
               <p>A sad case indeed; it was my case, I am as you are, a <hi>Lay man,</hi> as some call us, ignorant enough, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">An. </seg>
                  </label> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Parson</hi> nor <hi>Vicar,</hi> nor Lawyer neither, yet I thank God I have found a way to resolve the case ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, both touching the <hi>holy way, and warre.</hi> I will tell you how (yet I will not recall what was said before, which is the main <hi>[aske counsell at Gods mouth]</hi> how I have guided my steps in these per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed and troublous times, to find out a <hi>right way</hi> and a <hi>just</hi> warre. I observed narrowly, which way the Divel goes (his foot-steps are manifest) which way the Pope, Cardinals, Jesuites, all the bloodie Rogues in Ireland, all the <hi>noble monsters</hi> in England (as the Heathen cals them, who are Noble in their birth, and ignoble in their life) which way all the <hi>Bishops,</hi> all the Priests, those <hi>droves</hi> and <hi>beards</hi> of men, whom some call <hi>Ministers,</hi> the Scripture cals <hi>dumbe dogs, brutish Pastors,</hi> which way these went, and all the <hi>brutish</hi> people. I observed too, which way your <hi>Lawyers</hi> went, who could grinde the faces of the poore, turning judgement into gall, and Justice into wormewood. I observed narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which way all these went, and I discovered it as plainly as you might discern that mans Nose, which was so over-growne, that it covered halfe his face, so plainly. Then I <hi>discoursed,</hi> I reasoned out my way; a very little Logick (Reason) did serve the turne, even so much as a <hi>dogge</hi> hath; he will smell here, and there, and then he <hi>concludes</hi> very <hi>logically</hi> (sayes one) which is his way, and away he runs. So much or a very little more reason, will serve any man to reason-out his way here; thus, will the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell and his servants go a <hi>way</hi> to destroy their own kingdom? I know they will in the close and issue of their day and work; But their intendment and grand designe is, to build-up their kingdom, to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish their <hi>true Protestant Religion</hi> (Popery) as it <hi>was in Queene Maries dayes.</hi> Reasoning thus, I concluded, my way; not to go the way of the <hi>destroyer,</hi> where wasting and destruction is; not to go the way the Divel goes, the Pope and all his Bishops: not to fight my selfe into slavery. Me thought I did abhorre the very thought of such away, to shew my self a <hi>fool,</hi> a <hi>knave,</hi> an Irish or English Rogue, to destroy my own Countrey; to kill them, who would save me; to pluck down that house, which would build-up mine; to eat out the bowels of my own mother. Truly (I speak in Gods eare) I did abhorre the thought of that way. And so I concluded the <hi>Right way.</hi> Now touching the <hi>warre,</hi> I helped my self herein thus▪ The King cals in to his side; the Parliament cals in to their side. A mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable case, two parties in one Kingdom! Yes, and no strange thing, so it hath been ever since there were two Brothers in the world: I <hi>discoursed</hi> upon it, and reasoned the Case, to <hi>which party shall I joyne?</hi> To that side, which makes a lawfull Warre. To find out this, I enquired diligently, what War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the King had, to call me forth to warre? It is boldnesse, you will say, to enquire into that matter. No, I have all the Law and Reason in the world for so doing. Will the King call me forth to go up to the kne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in blood, to hazard the shedding of my own blood too (but that is the smallest matter) to hazard my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight precious soul, which is more to me then all his th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdoms: And shall not I enquire into the <hi>Warrant?</hi> I have the Kings <hi>warrant,</hi> you will say. I know that as well as you, and did know it since the day he first set up his <hi>Stan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ard</hi> But his W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrant can stand me in no stead: nor can it serve his own turn neither. I must have such a <hi>Warrant,</hi> so should he too, which will bear me out not at Oxford, but before the Throne in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aven, such a warrant I must have; but such a <hi>Warrant</hi> the Kings is not. It will not be a Warrant for himself before the highest Throne, that he hath <hi>Araied</hi> three Kingdoms by Authority from his <hi>immediate Warrant:</hi> God be thanked we may read it in Print, His Majestie (in the power of most pernicious Councellors) doth not onely call his loyall Subjects forth to warre, but to vow and protest, <hi>That his warre is lawfull;</hi> no, but they will not, they will be hanged first, or be starved to death, and that is worse (as they have been many a one.) For where or what is the Warrant? I pray you read it si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h it is annexed to these Papers: His Majestie (seduced by most wicked Councell) will <hi>Aray (i. e.)</hi> set three Kingdoms in a posture of Warre. By what Warrant? It is told you, <hi>By expresse Warrant of his Majesty:</hi> or by <hi>Authority derived from his Majesties immediate Warrant.</hi> If it be sense take it. The Lord Keeper is <hi>drunk</hi> sure enough, not with wine, wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess; but with a worse drunkennesse. <hi>Immediate Warrant!</hi> What a word is that? It belongs to God, to do so, God of gods, and <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Lords.</hi> And yet he doth not do so. When he made warre with all the world, all the world should know how Just it was; He would manage it justly; He would, to teach
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159067:14"/> man (a creature very subject to passion, and very full of <hi>self-will,</hi> to teach man what to do) <hi>consult</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it; He did <hi>consult</hi> about the framing of Man, that admirall fabrick, He was pleased to <hi>consult</hi> about the taking-down the destroying of that building. <hi>God came down to see whether things</hi> were indeed according <hi>to the cry. Chrysostome</hi> hath excellent observations thereupon, but I passe them over, the point is this; there is a <hi>we</hi> about it, <hi>God</hi> doth not do it alone, he consults about it. In particular cases, the Lord, the high God hath done nothing, but what He hath communicated to His friends first. God hath a Prerogative Royall, which man must not dispute; But yet, when God inflicts judgements upon a people, He will give that people Reasons thereof, so as His people shall say, <hi>The Lord is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> It doth not belong to a man, though a King, to say, I will bring a devouring plague upon a Land, I will bathe <hi>the Sword in Heaven,</hi> my <hi>will</hi> shall be Reason sufficient. But so a King saies, and so he does, when he <hi>Araies</hi> a Kingdom, commands them to take up Armes by his <hi>own expresse War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or by Authority derived from his own Immediate Warrant. (i. e.)</hi> from his own immediate <hi>will.</hi> This were worth the standing upon, but I have done with it; it is a proud word, little short of Blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. Nay, examine it well, you will find it upright Blasphemy, it goes very high, if this doth so; <hi>I will ascend above the heighth of the clouds,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Isa. 14.</note>
                  <hi>I will be like the most High.</hi> The King ascends higher, he sets himself above God, if you note the word well. Then I concluded, <hi>The Kings Warre is most unjust;</hi> it hath no <hi>Warrant</hi> from <hi>Law,</hi> but onely from his <hi>will,</hi> biased by his Judgement, corrupted and steeped in Affection. By the Rule of contraries, the Parliaments war is the Just war, they have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised about it, taken counsell at Gods mouth, and His Law-book, and so have <hi>Araied</hi> the Kingdome by Authority of Parliament <hi>(i. e.)</hi> by the Authority of the King ruling not <hi>immediately</hi> by his <hi>meer Will,</hi> but by the <hi>Lavv</hi> in his Court of Parliament. This is sufficient to shew the <hi>infallability</hi> of the <hi>vvay</hi> and Justice of the <hi>Warre,</hi> that observing as aforesaid, it is not possible we should be deceived in it. Now I call God to Record upon my soul, that I have shewed my Countrey men the <hi>Way</hi> they must go; and what side, they must joyne themselves unto, if they will shew themselves reasonable men. And if so be any man will object more against this, as I will not chide with him, so I will not answer him, but passe him-by, a brutish man, content to go in the <hi>vvay of Cain,</hi> who slew his Brother; And to give forth his hand, and <hi>Aray</hi> himself for the Warre, by Warrant of a Kings <hi>meer vvill,</hi> with the Irish Rogues and English Monsters, to destroy their King, and lay waste the Kingdom. Here is one Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection more against the whole Parliament, which commands Answer.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> But now I warrant you, the Parliament repent of what they have done; because they now see such Tumults, about the Covenant.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ans. </seg>
                  </label> I assure thee, Reader, I have heard a wise man say as much; but I thought him, (and without breach of charity) a fool for saying thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margDblQuotes">If the Parliament had knowne what would have followed, they would not have don as they did. What a peice of folly is this?</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is as if he had said; If <hi>Moses</hi> had knowne the deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> would have caused such stirres, then the people should have continued there for <hi>Moses:</hi> And if <hi>Joshua</hi> had knowne before, how high the Cities walls in <hi>Canaan</hi> were, and what Sonnes of <hi>Anak</hi> were there, he would never have taken that office upon him, to goe before the people thitherward. And if <hi>Elijah</hi> had known how mad Queen <hi>Jezabel</hi> would be at the hearing, what he had don to <hi>Baal,</hi> and his <hi>Servitors</hi> all, he would never have slaine them with the Sword. A Bug-beare to fright children! Tell the servant of the <hi>Lord,</hi> him who is jealous for a jealous God, tell him, that a Lion is in the way, some great difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, he is not daunted, he will go-on in his way, rather Gods way, the more resolutely, and stoutly, for when Reason has no bottom to stand upon, Faith has. But to the Objection. If the Parliament had knowne, that the Devill would have so raged, and his servants, imagining a vaine thing, would have made Tumults. What then? Then they would not have entered Covenant with their God, nor have given forth their hand to set up the Lord Christ on his Throne; nor have pressed on the People to be helpfull therein. I say againe, what a peice of folly is here! True it is; When wee see the issue of things, wee ought to reflect upon our actions, and though those may be unquestionable, yet wee may ponder well, the manner of our performance of them; So we may do, and finde fault enough, and ground of repentance. And so touching the Covenant. But never see cause of repentance, that wee entered into it, and enjoyned the People of the Land so to do. For what is fallen out now, which was not exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted? The Devill rageth now, and his servants make tumults: Yes. And there is not a sober man in the world, but expected so much, and they looke upon all this rage and these tumults, as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrative Argument, to shew that the Covenant is <hi>holy, just,</hi> and <hi>good;</hi> They are glad to heare and see this with all their hearts; What? To heare Devils roare, and his servants rage; they are glad of that, and expected so much; The <hi>Dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll is pinched now</hi> (said <hi>Luther</hi> once) now I pray you, give him leave to roare now, and his Subjects to rage; They have but a very short time; their Kingdome is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159067:14"/> smitten-at, it must downe. Downe, you will say! Men fall, and Cities fall, and you say the Devills Kingdome goes downe. Yes, I say so indeed, and will stand to what I say. There is an <hi>Earth-quake</hi> now, and now wee must looke to see <hi>a falling,</hi> but our <hi>falling</hi> shall be to <hi>rise</hi> againe. The Devills Kingdome falls now, and shall fall like a Mill-stone, never to <hi>rise</hi> againe. You must give him leave to roare, and his servants to rage, and not thinke it any strange matter. Every man that has heard, or read the Scripture, can tell himselfe as strange a thing as this; He reads of a People full of <hi>wrath,</hi> and <hi>crying out,</hi> and <hi>their whole Citie filled with confusion;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 19.</note> and the men there <hi>Rushing</hi> upon the servants of the <hi>Lord,</hi> like mad men. Who or what were they? A Heathen People, very Children, as Atheists and Papists are now; But more excusable, for these are children now, though they are growne to ripe yeares; <hi>Children,</hi> (saith one) <hi>thinke Images to be men,</hi> Papists are verier fooles,<note place="margin">Illi simila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chra homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes putant esse, hi De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os: Illos aetas facit. Lact. li. <hi>1.</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for <hi>they thinke them to be gods.</hi> Such a conceit was here, and more then a conceit. And because onely this was said against these gods (for there was nothing don) <hi>That they be no gods which are made with hands,</hi> therefore were the People filled with rage, and all with confusion. A strange thing, you will say, that such a speech as this should cause such stirres: And yet it was not strange, that men are mad, when their gods are spoken against; which indeed <hi>Paul</hi> did do, though the wise Towne-Clerke said, <hi>That those things</hi> (meaning their gods) <hi>could not be spoken against.</hi> This was a peice of foolish policy, well becoming such a Towne-Clerke But this is to our purpose; Did <hi>Paul</hi> repent when he saw such an uproare, that he spake against their gods? No; his Spirit was the more <hi>stirred,</hi> and he would have entered in amongst these mad-men, but <hi>the Disciples withstood him,</hi> sayes the Text.<note place="margin">Acts 19.</note> They cannot do God service, who are not valiant for the truth, and the more resolved for His Cause, the more the Adversary is resolved to contend against it. The servants of the Lord must not recoyle backe, because the Adversary presseth on, for that is to give place to the Devill.</p>
               <p>One thing more remaines, I must put up a Petition in behalfe of my Countrey-men, to the house of Parliament. And because the matter and forme of it is to the heart of the People, it shall have not a word of reason in it, but the very <hi>sense</hi> of the People.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <head>The humble Petition of the People inhabiting the <hi>Wild a Kent,</hi> and other Countreys, to the Honorable House of Commons.</head>
            <opener>Humbly sheweth;</opener>
            <p>THat it was well with your Petitioners, when, like People like Priests, they would goe to the Ale-house with us, sit there till Church time, then wee hast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thither, he to reade and wee to heare <hi>Divine Service.</hi> After that was don, to riott againe. Wee could then [offer Cakes to the Queen of Heaven <hi>(i. e.]</hi> serve the gods, pleasures and profits, that were most pleasing and serviceable to us, and heare no reproofe for doing so, [though we walkt in wayes best pleasing in our own Eyes; [loose with God, and in fast Covenant with sinne, death, and hell.] It was well with us then, for wee had plenty of victualls, and saw no evill; Now wee are consumed with the Sword. Our hearty Petition is, that, in due Consideration of the Premises, you would be pleased to give us our Bishops a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine [who thought no more of Preaching, then the Cobler does of Plowing; had no more care of souls then of their old shooes] and our <hi>Service-Booke,</hi> so full of good Prayers, there wee have them by heart, as well as our Bishop, and can say them, as will serve the turne, and as our Parson does, though halfe asleepe, or quite drunke. And for our Charter, wee heartily pray you take not that from us, wee received an <hi>Advouson</hi> of <hi>Libertie,</hi> to drinke and daunce on the Sunday, a time designed by our good Bishop, and by us, for that very purpose: And by no meanes urge us with a <hi>Covenant,</hi> wee cannot stand to it. Besides, wee are not resolved how lawfull it is; for our Bishop, a very good Church-man, and a good fellow also, would never lay such bands upon us, nor endure them himselfe. Wee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159067:15"/> pray you heartily, give us such Bishops, and our <hi>Service Booke,</hi> and deny us not that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and <hi>Living</hi> wee have the <hi>Advouson</hi> of; We will a grace a God, observe our Church in our C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rch-time, those are two houres in the Day, as we are told. The remaining time is our; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd wee pray you yet more heartily, give us <hi>Peace,</hi> that good thing, that we may plough, sow, and reape, a <hi>Peace</hi> of your owne making, and giving; Wee know not of whom else to aske it: And for <hi>Truth,</hi> so much talked of, what is it? Gtve us peace, that wee may walke loose and as free-men, so wee shall pray for you, and blesse you too; <hi>Blessed be yee of the Lord, you had compassion on us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly, if my head were a Fountaine, I would weepe over these; and if my heart were as it should be, I would sigh out my words, <hi>Poore Soules, Poore Soules;</hi> They can now as <hi>Saul</hi> once, Count that a Compassion, which tends to the destruction of Body and Soule for ever. <hi>Poore Soules, Poore Soules!</hi> for want of knowledge these must perish. I have concluded two yeares agoe, nay, ever since I could observe the Bishop and his People, That <hi>Bishops</hi> and the <hi>Service Booke,</hi> are the cause of all this bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish ignorance, which has so over-spread the Countries, and made them <hi>Wilde.</hi> By the helpe of God His hand with mee, I shall make this Charge good, and settle upon it presently, now that I have don with this, and cleared to all the world, who are not wilfully blind, That our Covenant is <hi>holy, just,</hi> and <hi>good.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="covenant">
            <head>OXFORDS Oath or Covenant to be taken by all His Majesties loyall Subjects, for the maintenance of the true Reformed Protestant Religion, his Majesties just Rights, and the Priviledge of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Resting fully assured of his Majesties Princely truth and goodnesse, do freely and from my heart promise, vow, and protest in the presence of Almighty God, that I will to the uttermost of my power, and with the hazard of my life maintaine the true Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion established in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> his Majesties sacred person, his Heires and lawfull Successors, his Majesties just power and priviledge, and the just power and priviledge of Parliament, against the Forces under the conduct of the Earle of <hi>Essex,</hi> and against all other Forces whatsoever, contrary to his Majesties command, and I doe beleeve that the raysing and employing of Forces by his Majesty for the purpose and cause before mentioned, to be most just and necessary; and I will do my utmost endeavour to procure and <hi>re-establish the peace and quiet of the Kingdome: and that herein his Majesties Subjects may fully enjoy their liberty and property, according to the Law of the Land,</hi> and will neither divulge nor communicate any thing to the said Earle, his officers, or to any other, to hinder or prejudice the designes of his Majesty, in the conduct or imployment of his Army, and I doe beleeve the Subjects of <hi>England</hi> are not obliged <hi>by any Act of State,</hi> Vote, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaance, or Declaration <hi>made</hi> or to be made, either <hi>by the Kings Majesty solely,</hi> or by <hi>the Lords and Commons</hi> singly or joyntly, <hi>without his Majesties expresse consent,</hi> saving such as are, or shall be in execution of, or according to some knowne Law, Custome of the Realme, or Statute enacted by the King, Lords and Commons in Parliament, and I doe further protest &amp; vow in the presence of Almighty God, that I will not take nor beare Arms, but by the expresse warrant of his Majesty, or by Authoritie justly derived from his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties immediate Warrant.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>